<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for the non-conformists tending to justifie them against the clamorous charge of schisme. By a Dr. of Divinity. With two sheets on the same subject by another Hand and Judgement.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3703A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1868:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for the non-conformists tending to justifie them against the clamorous charge of schisme. By a Dr. of Divinity. With two sheets on the same subject by another Hand and Judgement.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 90, [2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A Dr. of Divinity = John Humfrey.</note>
                  <note>"An account of the non-conformists meetings for divine worship, by, Mr. H. according to his Middle-Way, and against Dean F's charge of schisme; .." is signed I. H. [i.e. John Humfrey] and has caption title, separate pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33146:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR THE <hi>NON-CONFORMISTS;</hi> TENDING To Juſtifie them againſt the Clamorous Charge of SCHISME.</p>
            <p>By a Dr. of Divinity.</p>
            <p>With two Sheets on the ſame Subject by another Hand and Judgment.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>exatio dat intellectum.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33146:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33146:2"/>
            <head>A PLEA for the <hi>Nonconformiſts;</hi> tending to juſtifie them againſt the Clamourous Charge of Schiſme.</head>
            <p>§. 1. IT was doubtleſs one of the greateſt infelicities which ever befel the whole body of people in theſe three Nations (conſidering them as univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally profeſſing the Doctrine of Chriſt), that in the year 1662. the Settlement of the affairs of Religion, with relation to <hi>Worſhip</hi> &amp; <hi>Government,</hi> was made to no more univerſal ſatisfaction, but that ſome thouſands of Miniſters, many of whom (their greateſt Adverſaries being judges) were men of no inconſiderable worth and uſefulneſs, took themſelves obliged rather to lay down the publick
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33146:3"/>exerciſe of their Miniſtry, then to do what was by Law required of them, if they would preſerve it; and that ſuch a rigid interpretation was at that time in practice, put upon the Act of Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as they were not only incapacita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to hold, or take Livings, but alſo to Preach occaſionally in the publick Temples. Whether the Act will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate any ſuch ſenſe, may deſerve the ſecond thoughts of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</p>
            <p>§. 2. Whether this was Originated in the anger reſting in the boſom of ſome Church-men at that time, who had been Sufferers: Or in their zeal to continue ſome Biſhops the repute of Martyrs, who had ſuffered for the rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enforcing of ſome of the things now enjoyned, or in the deſire of ſome of that <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> which ariſeth from <hi>pluralities</hi> of <hi>Livings, Dignities, ſine curare;</hi> or in their deſire to propagate ſome Doctrines, to which they knew the perſons who would be ejected, would be no more friends, then are the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33146:3"/>interpreted by King <hi>James,</hi> former all Profeſſors of Divinity in our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, very many eminent Biſhops, and once and again by the whole Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of <hi>England</hi>), or from one, or all of theſe cauſes is uncertain to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; a better Original is hard to fancy, while the things required, are by our moſt knowing Eccleſ. Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours granted <hi>not neceſſary,</hi> anteceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly to the Superiors command.</p>
            <p>§. 3. Nor could they ever have been <hi>made neceſſary</hi> (as is now ſaid) by the <hi>King and Parliament of</hi> England, had they not been ſuggeſted to them as things that in themſelves might <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be done:</hi> Nor (probably) would that ſuggeſtion have prevailed with our civil Superiours, (who in things meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawful, know ſufficiently that they are to govern themſelves in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands by <hi>Prudence,</hi> had they not been alſo told that the Numbers both of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and People that would refuſe, were very inconſiderable. Their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and circumſtances very invaluable; that if once the things were enjoyned,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33146:4"/>the Generality would do them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their pretences of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 4. How true theſe ſuggeſtions were, quickly appeared to our Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent States-men, which made the then <hi>Lord Chancellour</hi> (a ſufficient friend to Conformity and a Prudent Perſon) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever the Act took place, ſend for ſome very valuable perſons, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound a <hi>Medium</hi> to them that they might yet abide in their ſtations (fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the gap would be made) the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes only providing ſome who might read the Liturgy; but this was too late, and the Act would not, when it came out, admit any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>§. 5. With that rigour the Act was preſſed, is ſufficiently known, and how ſoon after fortified with another Act againſt <hi>private Meetings;</hi> and with another (when that but a probationer for a few years was expired) more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere than the former; nor did there want thoſe in all parts of the Nation, that executed all the Acts with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſo far beyond what thoſe Acts Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33146:4"/>that they ſaw need of Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for their actions by further <hi>Acts of Grace and Favour.</hi> How many God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters and People, were, during theſe years, not only publickly reviled in Pamphlets and Pulpits, but Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned (and how many dyed in their impriſonments) ſpoiled of their Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, driven from their Habitations and Trades, is but an unpleaſant ſtory to reflect upon, and with how little ſucceſs as to the bringing them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form is abundantly known.</p>
            <p>§. 6. In the mean time it pleaſed his <hi>moſt Excellent Majeſty</hi> (as a tender Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his People, and he who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his intereſt lay not in the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Ruine of his People, but in their Peace and Freedom to attend their ſeveral Trades, Profeſſions and Callings (the King himſelf, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, being nouriſhed from the Field) to inſpect the ſtate of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical affairs; and hearing ſo many Crys from his People, with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Counſel to direct means for his or their better information, about
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33146:5"/>the numbers of Miniſters and People diſſenting; for which purpoſe <hi>Letters</hi> were directed in the ordinary courſe from the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who by their Regiſters were to inform themſelves, and then his moſt <hi>Sacred Majeſty</hi> of the Number of diſſenting Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 7. How imperfect the informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be in this method is obvious enough to every one; the Return could only be made of thoſe, who being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of Livings, <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. 1662. left them for not Subſcribing, into which number came not a 5th. part of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters diſſenting.
<list>
                  <item>1. None came, which 1661 were turned out to give room to others, who had a praevious Title to their Livings, and were not poſſeſt ſo ſoon of any other, which were very many.</item>
                  <item>2. No Congregational Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who had no Legal Titles to Churches.</item>
                  <item>3. None that fore-ſeeing they could not conform (the Act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out) did chuſe rather to reſign their Livings than abide a turning out.</item>
                  <item>4. No young men, not poſſeſt of Livings,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33146:5"/>though ready for them: To ſay nothing of <hi>Anabapt.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
To advantage this imperfect account, the <hi>Author of the Eccleſiaſtical Polity</hi> tells the World of but an <hi>hundred Miniſters,</hi> that hindred all Uniformity.</p>
            <p>§. 8. But our Wiſe and Prudent States-men quickly ſaw through theſe Fallacies, and from their more perfect information of his moſt <hi>Sacred Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>meltings of his own bowels</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the diſtreſſes of his People; the ſound of which, came almoſt from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Court of Judicature, and corner of the Nation, his <hi>moſt Excellent Majeſty</hi> and his <hi>Privy Counſel</hi> took a fuller eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of the Number both of Miniſters and private Chriſtians diſſenting from the publick modes of worſhip.</p>
            <p>§. 9. Upon this, it was that his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> (conceiving himſelf empowred thereto by his Prerogative, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty reſerved to him by the laſt <hi>Act</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Conventicles,</hi>) was pleaſed to iſſue out his Gracious <hi>Declaration for Indulgence,</hi> date, <hi>Mar.</hi> 17.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33146:6"/>
            <p>§. 10. What Power his Majeſty had, or what was reſerved by that Act, to him, we are no Judges to determine. It is enough for us, That as his <hi>moſt Sacred Majeſty</hi> hath aſſerted to himſelf ſuch a power, ſo the denial of it to him, hath been by no publick Act made known to us, much leſs his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties receſſion from it, Diſputes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Kings and Parliaments,</hi> we think, are not to be determined by private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons without the doors of the <hi>Pallace</hi> and <hi>Parliament-Houſe,</hi> nor medled with by the Subject, till the matters in difference (if any be) be agreed by themſelves, and by ſome publick acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on notified to the People. We know for the King of <hi>England</hi> in civil things, to ſuſpend the execution of an Act which he hath found inconveniently practicable till the <hi>Parliaments meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and further agreeing in it, is no more than hath been done even during this Parliament, and poſſibly to all may not appear unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>§. 11. Upon this foundation we ſtand, and practice, Preaching to our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33146:6"/>People in places diſtinct from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Churches. What can we do leſs? May we, having this liberty, ſit ſtill, and live without the publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God? Thus indeed a very great number of the People of <hi>England</hi> (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly not inferiour to the N. Con.) yet we have rarely heard of one of them Endited, Preſented, or Proſecuted, when our Brethren were in their fulleſt career againſt the new Recuſants, at leaſt, not comparably to thoſe of their Brethren, who they knew were every Sabbath day (if not with them, yet ſomewhere ſtrictly worſhipping God, and either Preaching Chriſt, or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Preach'd. Surely our eager Men ſhould rather have bent their Bows, and made their Arrows ready a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe Atheiſtical livers, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Servants of the Living God, though of a little different Livery; different too, not in the Cloath, but in the inſignificant <hi>Fringes</hi> and <hi>Laces</hi> of formes and ceremonies. What though they could ſay (which we know in truth they cannot) that <hi>Chriſt</hi> (amongſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33146:7"/>the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi>) was <hi>Preached of envy and ſtrife,</hi> yet had they been of St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Spirit (from whom they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to derive, though indeed Chriſt, amongſt the <hi>Noncon.</hi> had been Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Contention, and not of Sincerity.</hi> (Yet a little charity would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to judge as <hi>Paul, Some out of good will Preached</hi> him.) But however they being (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18. <hi>Set for the defence of the Goſpel,</hi> ſhould have ſaid after him, <hi>What then? Notwithſtanding every way, whether in pretence, or in truth Chriſt is Preached, and I therein do rejoyce, and will rejoyce:</hi> We ſhall only ſay, had they been of St. <hi>Pauls Spirit,</hi> they would have ſaid ſo.</p>
            <p>§. 12. We take it to be a confeſſed Principle; <hi>That every individual Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church-Catholick Viſible, is bound in duty both to God and his own Soul, to joyn himſelf to ſome particular Society of Chriſtians, with which he may enjoy all the Ordinances of God, ſo as may be for his Souls advantage.</hi> What ſhall therefore theſe indulged Miniſters and People do? How ſhall they live
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33146:7"/>up to this peice of the Divine Will? <hi>Shall they joyn with the Parochial Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in their Temples?</hi> They have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to the World, that the buſineſs is ſo ſtated by <hi>the Act of Uniformity,</hi> that they cannot do this without doing what they judge ſinful. If they could, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would the Miniſters 1662. have parted, together with that publick exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their Miniſtry, with the liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods alſo of themſelves, their Wives &amp; Children; or expoſed themſelves to <hi>Excommunications, Impriſonments, Fines, Baniſhments,</hi> and all manner of Reproach and Obloquy, or their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to the Charitable Baskets of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Neither would more private Chriſtians have ſuffered ſo much in moſt of theſe kinds, as they have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in vain.</p>
            <p>§. 13. It muſt therefore be in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, <hi>locally ſeparate from the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial meetings.</hi> Accordingly, having firſt obtained his Majeſtie's Licenſes they practice. Preſently they hear a great Out-cry of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and <hi>ſinful ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> from <hi>true Churches, Gathering Churches out of Churches,</hi> and we know
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33146:8"/>not what, nor do we believe they do, that clamour at this rate.</p>
            <p>§. 14. But the truth of this clamour muſt be a little examined; for the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> have got very little by his Majeſties favour, by eſcaping <hi>the hands of men,</hi> to <hi>fall into the hands of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi> We remember when <hi>David</hi> was in his great ſtrait, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.14. he acquieſſed in this. <hi>Let me fall into the hands of the living God, for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are great, and let me not fall into the hands of men.</hi> We think we may (in this caſe) ſay the ſame thing, and that with ſome advantage (which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had not, for his heart ſmote him for a known ſin, our hearts as yet do not condemn us for any ſuch black thing as a <hi>ſinful ſeparation;</hi> and we do believe thoſe that thus clamour do not well underſtand what they ſay. Let men rather call us <hi>Schiſmaticks, ſinful Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts,</hi> ſo we may worſhip God as his Word, and our own Conſciences tells us he ſhould be Worſhipped purely, and in <hi>Spirit and Truth,</hi> rather than we not Worſhip God at all, or ſo as our Conſciences ſhall continually flie in our faces.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33146:8"/>
            <p>§. 15. But certainly God's Word hath laid us under no neceſſity of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; let us therefore challenge our confident Accuſers <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony.</hi> 'Tis worth the while to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether this great cry be not <hi>Vox et praeterea nihil;</hi> A clamorous ſcandal &amp; nothing elſe, which we are the more advantaged to hope that it will prove by a noted paſſage in a great <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> his <hi>diſcourſe of Schiſme.</hi> It is this, <hi>Schiſme is one of thoſe Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scare-Crowes, with which, they who uſe to uphold a party in Religion, uſe to fright away ſuch as make any inquiry into it, and are ready to relinquiſh or oppoſe it, if it appeareth to them either erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or ſuſpicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that <hi>Schiſme,</hi> truly ſo called, is of no graver importance, but that which generally by <hi>School-men</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> and very many (and ſome of thoſe Learned) Divines (though like <hi>Elias,</hi> men ſubject to like paſſions with other men) is no more, is as evident as the ſhining of the Sun at Noon-day, to any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33146:9"/>one who knoweth any thing of Books, or of the World.</p>
            <p>§. 16. The <hi>Greeks,</hi> ſay thoſe of the Latine Church, are <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and they (becauſe they are the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church) ſeem to have beſt right; but the whole <hi>Latine</hi> Church requites them with the ſame-name of Obloquy. The <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſo call the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> but they requite them with the like term, ſaying, <hi>They that gave the cauſe of the ſeparation, are the true Schiſmaticks.</hi> Amongſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> ſo revile the <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> nor are the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> behind them, Amongſt the <hi>Calviniſts.</hi> The <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> men ſo call the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſo call the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paedebaptiſts.</hi> Thus we have called one another <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> round. Let us therefore leave theſe pittiful, unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, Boyiſh Revenges, eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vulgar uſe lately, the term hath had no further ſignificancy than to ſpeak perſons not of our mind, and for a name to brand ſuch of our Brethren with, who are a little more inquiſitive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33146:9"/>than others into the things of God, and is of the ſame import amongſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants;</hi> that the word <hi>Heretick</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Papiſts, that is <hi>not one of their mind;</hi> and leaving terms of reviling to the Women at <hi>Billings-gate,</hi> we will fairly ſtate the Caſe, and argue it as coolely.</p>
            <p>§. 17. The Queſtion is this, <hi>Whether the Non-conforming Miniſters, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple meeting ordinarily together for the Worſhip of God, in Aſſemblies and places locally diſtinct and ſeparate from the meetings of the Parochial Congregations, becauſe the ſaid Miniſters may not Preach there, nor the ſaid people enjoy there all the Ordinances of God without the doing of ſome things which their Conſciences upon Arguments which they judge highly probable, do judge ſinful, be what</hi> the Scripture calleth Schiſme, <hi>or be in any right Reaſon</hi> A ſinful Separation; <hi>theſe perſons in the mean time not condemning all</hi> Parochial <hi>Societies as no true Churches, nor in other things behaving themſelves uncharitably towards them,</hi> We muſt profeſs our ſelves to believe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33146:10"/>the <hi>Negative of this Queſtion,</hi> in which are two folded together. We affirm then
<list>
                  <item>1. This <hi>practice</hi> is not what <hi>The Scripture calls Schiſme.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Nor what right Reaſon, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from any Scriptural principles can call <hi>A ſinful Separation.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>We do grant there may be a ſinful Separation of Chriſtians <hi>from a Church,</hi> which the Scripture doth not call <hi>Schiſme,</hi> that maketh us diſtinguiſh theſe two things, nor ſhall we diſcourſe the former.
<list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe it <hi>is a plain</hi> Diſpute about a Term.</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe the eminently Learned Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> hath made it good, that a <hi>Separation from a Church</hi> (though it may be ſinful) yet is not that which the Scripture calls <hi>Schiſme;</hi> and we obſerve, that his very Learned Adverſary, upon the point, grants him this, and pleadeth for no more than an <hi>Analogical application of the term Schiſme, to expreſs the ſin of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary ſeparation from a Church,</hi> which we will not contend about.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33146:10"/>
            <p>§. 18. We ſay therefore, let it be <hi>ſo,</hi> or <hi>ſo,</hi> it is of no great conſequence; all grant there may be a <hi>ſinful ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from a Church,</hi> and if the ſeparation be not ſinful, we are ſure they Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name it that call it <hi>Schiſme.</hi> If it be ſinful, whether it ſhould be called <hi>Schiſme,</hi> or by ſome other name, we think ſignifieth very little to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of any intelligent Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>§. 19. Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> ſtill keeping the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect of the Schools, calls this <hi>ſinful ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> Schiſme, and gives us this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schiſme, is an unneceſſary ſeparation from that part of the Viſible Church, of which we once were Members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Like a wiſe man he ſpeaks, <hi>Multa paucis,</hi> remembring the <hi>Canon</hi> about Definitions. So then according to him to make a Schiſme.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There muſt be a ſeparation, and that not from the whole Viſible Church, (that is <hi>Hereſy</hi> or <hi>Apoſtacy</hi>) but from ſome part of it, of which we were once Members.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33146:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly:</hi> It muſt be an <hi>Unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſeparation</hi> that is where the Union might have been kept, without ſinning againſt God, we deſire no further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage than this Deſcription will give us, let our caſe ſtand or fall, as it will abide, or not abide this teſt.</p>
            <p>§. 20. Hence we argue, <hi>Where there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was an Union, or there is no ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or if there be a ſeparation, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, becauſe the Union could not be kept without ſin. There is no Schiſme</hi> but in the caſes of the Miniſters and People. <hi>Either there is no ſeparation, or there was no Union</hi> (which indeed ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed there could be no ſeparation) <hi>or no more than a neceſſary ſeparation; Ergo,</hi> No Schiſme, no ſinful ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>§. 21. To make good which, Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being a term of motion, before we can ſtrictly ſpeak to the parts of the Argument, we muſt enquire for the <hi>Term,</hi> from which this <hi>Motion,</hi> or <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> is pretended to be. The Author of <hi>The Doctrine of Schiſme,</hi> p. 40. tells us this roundly.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33146:11"/>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>'Tis a great and dangerous Schiſme, both againſt the Church of</hi> England <hi>and particular Churches.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>We will not quarrel with the Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Author for the propriety of that <hi>Engliſh,</hi>—a <hi>Schiſme againſt the Church</hi>—becauſe in the cloſe of the ſame page, though he doth not at all mend the matter (as to the poor Non-conformiſt, whom he was wont to own as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) yet he amendeth his Engliſh, telling us:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>If you conſider the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>as a particular Organized Church, 'tis a Schiſm from but as part of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Viſible Church only as the N. Con. uſe to term it, is a Schiſme in it;</hi>
               </q> and not only ſo, but p. 57. <q>
                  <hi>It is a Schiſme from particular Parochial Congregations:</hi>
               </q> For Mr. <hi>Candry</hi> (he ſaith) hath obſerved <q>
                  <hi>There was and is another Church-ſtate in our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregations.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 22. Here now is a double term, from which this motion is pretended to be.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Church of</hi> England.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Parochial Churches</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
To let
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33146:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>our Author know what we hold, we do believe a Catholick Viſible Church, which we take to be well deſcribed in the 19th. of the 39 Articles of our Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Congregation [or whole Body] of faithful men, in the which the pure Word of God is Preached, and the Sacraments are duly adminiſtred according to Chriſts Ordinance in all thoſe things that are of neceſſity requiſite to the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a part doubtleſs, and from the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this ſenſe we do not know that any have ſeparated, but ſuch as have <hi>renounced Chriſt and the Goſpel, or the Word and Ordinances ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation,</hi> which would be plain and deſperate Apoſtacy, with which, we hope our Brethren will be more modeſt than to charge us. From this our Plea is, we make <hi>no Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and therefore cannot be charged with a ſinful Separation. But ſaith our Author, <hi>You make a ſinful ſeparation in it.</hi> We are not troubled at words that ſignifie nothing, what is the meaning of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33146:12"/>this? Do we not Own <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> the ſame points of Faith, the ſame acts of Worſhip; where is the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then? Can all meet in the ſame place? It may be we do not pray by the ſame forms, nor ware the ſame habits, nor uſe ſome of thoſe rites ſome others of our Brethren uſe. Do our Brethren then always when they pray, uſe the ſame forms of words? Do not they take a liberty in the Pulpit? why may not we? Do other parts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church uſe the ſame forms? why elſe are not they Schiſmaticks? (for as yet we are only conſidering the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church of <hi>England</hi> as a part of the Church Catholick Viſible:) Is there any form, any habit, any rite or cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony commanded by Chriſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by us: if there be not, where is the Schiſme? It ſeems the term <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick,</hi> is their priviledge to uſe that can firſt get it out of their mouths; if we divide in no command of Chriſt, why may not the Non-Con. call their Brethren <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> as well as they call their Brethren? Doth an humane
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33146:13"/>Law create a difference? Let it be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried whether that can give a <hi>rule to Schiſme or no.</hi> What is the buſineſs then, how do we then <hi>make a Schiſme in the Church of</hi> England, conſidered as a part of the Church Catholick Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Do we break Charity with our Brethren? do we Revile them, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach their Perſons or Societies. Let them bear the blame who do it, we plead not for them; in the mean time, let not all other Non-Con. be called Schiſmaticks for their ſake. We know very many of the Non Con. have been uncharitably enough dealt with by thoſe three famous Authors of the <hi>Friendly debate, Eccleſiaſtical Polity,</hi> and of <hi>Knowledge of &amp; Communion with</hi> Chriſt, have they rendred <hi>reviling for reviling,</hi> though the Maſters of Morality have ſo treated their Brethren, as if <hi>Veracity, Comity,</hi> and <hi>Urbanity</hi> were not in the Catalogue of their <hi>Moral Virtues.</hi> When the Author opens himſelf a little plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and tells us what he meaneth by a <hi>Schiſme in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as a part of the Church. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33146:13"/>Viſible,</hi> we ſhall better underſtand him.</p>
            <p>§. 23. But he ſaith, we ſinfully ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>from the Organical National Church of</hi> England; and indeed this he muſt mean or nothing, by what he ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for it is not poſſible to ſeparate ſinfully from a <hi>National Church</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered only, as a large part of the Church-Catholick Viſibles, while they keep in the profeſſion of Chriſt and his Goſpel, and in the practice of the ſame Acts of worſhip with them, and in the ſame Doctrines of Faith, unleſs they fail in love, refuſing all kind of occaſional Communion with their Brethren, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning them as no parts of the Church of Chriſt. The worſhipping of God by different phraſes and forms of Prayers, in different habits of Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by different rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> will not do it, for theſe are things which belong not to any <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church</hi> as a part of the <hi>Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Viſible;</hi> Chriſt left no <hi>Liturgy</hi> to his Catholick Church, nor any ſuch rites and <hi>ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>habits;</hi> nor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33146:14"/>was ever the Catholick Viſible Church uniform in them; our Brethren them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſs theſe mutable things, wherein ſeveral parts of the Catholick Church differ each from other: Theſe things proceed from the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as Organical, not as a part of the <hi>Catholick Viſible Church;</hi> for then the major part of all particular Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt conſent to the impoſition of them.</p>
            <p>§. 24. Now truly for this <hi>Particular Organical National Church,</hi> it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we may have ſeparated from it, for we never knew there was any ſuch Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and at laſt our Author doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that Mr. <hi>Caudry</hi> hath told him that the Presbyterians do generally agree, <hi>That the Diſciplinary part or form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is not eſſential to a National Church;</hi> he ſhould therefore firſt have proved that there is ſuch a thing under the Goſpel as <hi>A Stated, National, Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Church;</hi> and we ſhould then have tried whether the ſame Arguments would not have ſerved the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to have proved a <hi>Catholick organical
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33146:14"/>Church,</hi> and that ſomething better than they ſerve our Author, becauſe they have found out a <hi>ſingle head</hi> for it, which we find our Author, <hi>p.</hi> 43. at great loſs to find for his <hi>particular Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Organical Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 95. He knows not whether he ſhould fix it upon the <hi>King,</hi> for he <hi>is to be conſidered as a mixed perſon:</hi> Or <hi>The Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is <hi>Primate of all</hi> England, or all the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Paſtors. That the King is the Supreme Political Head and Governour</hi> of the National Church of <hi>England,</hi> is our of doubt to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, but ſuch a one as will not claim Authority to any one ſtrictly called <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical act,</hi> neither to <hi>Preach, nor adminiſter a Sacrament,</hi> nor <hi>Ordain Miniſters.</hi> Are we diſcourſing of ſuch a head think we? The <hi>Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury indeed may do all theſe; but may he execute any acts of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in the Province of <hi>York?</hi> muſt the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>York</hi> be taken in. Then we have <hi>one National Church Organical</hi> with two heads; yet that is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33146:15"/>better than 26. for ſo many muſt be, if all the <hi>Biſhops</hi> make the head; and that yet is better than 9000 heads as muſt be, if the Paſtors of all Pariſhes be the Head. In ſhort, none of theſe can by an act of Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the whole body; and what kind of head is that? The King indeed (as Political Head of the Church) may influence the whole with his commands, relating to Eccleſiaſtical affairs; but ſurely we have no <hi>Arçh-Biſhop, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> or <hi>Paſtor,</hi> can Excommunicate from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſhaba.</hi> Our Author not being able to fix his thoughts in this point, at laſt tells us, <hi>It is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, for it is a certain Vanity to ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">43.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe I cannot find the the Head, I will deny the Body.</hi> Is it ſo? <hi>can there then be a living Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganical Body without an Head?</hi> It is not the body we are diſcourſing of, but an <hi>Organical Body:</hi> We may know our Mother (as our Author ſaith) though we do not know our Father; but we muſt know we had a Father, and that Father is, or was a viſible Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33146:15"/>or elſe he could not be known.</p>
            <p>§. 26. Well, but what is this ſame <hi>National Organical Church</hi> of England. He <hi>p.</hi> 42. gives us this Deſcription of it:</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>It is a community conſiſting of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſtians united in the ſame Doctrine, Government and Worſhip, according to the 39. Articles, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, her Liturgy, and Canons, and Laws, and divided into Parochial Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, for the more convenient Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 45 <q>
                  <hi>Schiſme from the Church of</hi> England <hi>is a ſinful dividing from, or diſſolving our Union or Communion with her in her Governours, Worſhip, Members, or Aſſemblies.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>We can neither allow his deſcriptis on of the National Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor yet of his deſcription of Schiſme, or ſinful ſeparation from it, and we would gladly hear by what Scripture or reaſon, either of them can be made good.</p>
            <p>§. 27. It will be no wonder if deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing of a <hi>National Governing Church,</hi> we deny the deſcription of it,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33146:16"/>for <hi>Non eus, non poteſt definiri;</hi> Now we do believe that under the Goſpel there never was, nor can be a <hi>ſtated Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional governing Church,</hi> unleſs what is indeed ſomtimes, though far from the ſenſe we are now ſpeaking to, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not ſo properly called a <hi>Church,</hi> according to the dialect of Scripture made up of all the Meſſengers of all the particular Churches in a Nation, in an Aſſembly for deliberations, advice, and determinations in ſome weighty emergent caſes, to obviate which, we put in the term <hi>ſtated,</hi> for this is only an <hi>Occaſional National Church,</hi> or <hi>Synod,</hi> which hath but a temporary being <hi>pro renatâ,</hi> and meets and acts at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>Prince,</hi> the Supreme Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Head.</p>
            <p>§. 28. When we ſpeak of a Church, we underſtand Church as a Scriptural term in the Religious uſage of it, appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to no body of people, but ſuch a one as the Scripture calleth ſo. So that if there be any ſuch body as may be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>National Governing Organical Church,</hi> we muſt either find it in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33146:16"/>
               <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> or at leaſt find ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections there for the conſtitution &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of it, ſome Commiſſions given for a ſucceſſion of National Officers, but we find none of this; we find indeed a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral commiſſion to Miniſters to go and <hi>Preach</hi> and <hi>Baptize;</hi> but this referred as well to the Heathens, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſtians. If any will ſay that the Apoſtles were <hi>General Officers,</hi> and from thence will argue for a ſucceſſion of them, it will better ſerve the Papiſts to prove an <hi>Univerſal Organical Church,</hi> than it will ſerve any to prove a <hi>National Organical Church;</hi> and we think that is what our Brethren will not be very free of granting. If any urge the Example of the <hi>Jewiſh National Church,</hi> which was <hi>Organical,</hi> they will be alſo obliged to find our Saviours directions for the Hereditary diſcent of an <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> or the Election of one into his place. We always thought the Jewiſh <hi>H. Prieſt</hi> was a type, and Chriſt the <hi>Antitype,</hi> whoſe coming aboliſhed the type, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that that alſo will prove an <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Organical Church,</hi> for the Jewiſh
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33146:17"/>High Prieſt govern'd the whole Viſible Church, which God in his days had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth; beſides we muſt have found ſome rules and laws left us by Chriſt for this <hi>High Prieſt.</hi> Finally, who ſo will erect a <hi>ſtated National go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning or Organical</hi> Church in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> muſt find us an <hi>Officer</hi> cloathed with Authority to Excommunicate from <hi>Michaels Mount</hi> in <hi>Cornwall</hi> to <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile</hi> and <hi>Berwick.</hi> Such a one we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there neither is, nor ever was in <hi>England</hi> ſince the reformation.</p>
            <p>§. 29. But if we could allow ſuch a Creature of God as a <hi>National govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church in</hi> England, we ſhould have put <hi>Governours</hi> (being certainly one of the Eſſential parts of ſuch a Church) into the deſcription of it, as well as into the Notion of <hi>Schiſme</hi> from it. Nor ſhould we have ſo ſtraitned the Notion of it, as to neceſſitate all the members of it to be united in <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> without ſaying how far they muſt in theſe things be united. Whether in every point of Doctrine delivered in the <hi>39. Articles</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:33146:17"/>ſo far as to approve and embrace all. And in every point of <hi>Government,</hi> according to the <hi>Canons;</hi> or in every mode, rite, or <hi>ceremony</hi> according to the Liturgy; or if not, in what, and how far they muſt be thus united? And for the Laws (as diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Canons,</hi>) we ſhould have left them quite out, being but civil conſtitutions, about the affairs of the Church, not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Laws of the Church, or in the more intrinſick matters of it; but <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus cuncta male miniſtrat,</hi> this is the unlucky effect of long <hi>Definitions,</hi> and too great eagerneſs to prove all <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> Schiſmaticks. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſhould have done well to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered what he, as well as we long ſince learned at the Univerſity.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones debent eſſe breves.</hi> It is the length of this deſcription that ſpoils it, and makes it by no art defenſible.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Debet conſtare ex attributis preoribus &amp; notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus ſimpliciter,</hi> had this been thought of the 39 <hi>Articles, Homilies, Liturgy, Canons, Laws,</hi> had been quite left out; nor certainly did our Author conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33146:18"/>what would follow upon this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>§. 30. Let us but a little ſhew what inferences follow his Deſcription of the <hi>National Governing Church of</hi> England. 1. <hi>All Arminians</hi> without bail or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe muſt be Hereticks. They are none of the <hi>Community of profeſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in</hi> England, <hi>united in the Doctrine of the</hi> 39 <hi>Articles;</hi> will they tell us they are? Let us ask King <hi>James,</hi> once the very learned <hi>Head of this Church.</hi> He tell us.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>That</hi> Arminians <hi>was an Enemy to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reg. Jacobi <hi>Dec. contra Vorſtium,</hi> p. 12. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>that his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are Peſts, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Arrogant perſons, Sectaries, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That the very Title of <hi>Bertius</hi> his Book, concerning the <hi>Apoſtacy of the Saints,</hi> required the fire. Shall we be judged by the <hi>Parliament</hi> (they make the <hi>Laws</hi> put into the deſcription of this Church) they confirmed the <hi>Articles:</hi> We find them <hi>Anno</hi> 1628. crying aloud, <q>
                  <hi>We Claim, Proteſt, and avow
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33146:18"/>for Truth, the ſenſe of the Articles of Religion, which were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by Parliament,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, <hi>p.</hi> 650.</note> 130. Eliz. <hi>which (ſay they) by the Publick Act of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and by the general and currant expoſition of the Writers of our Church, have been delivered to us; and we reject the ſenſe of the</hi> Jeſuits <hi>and</hi> Arminians, <hi>and all others where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ from us.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Shall we ask the <hi>Profeſſors of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> forty years ſince and upward in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Univerſity: They joyntly agreed theſe points contrary to the 39 Articles (one Dr. <hi>Baro</hi> only excepted), and we know who was the firſt <hi>Doctor</hi> of that <hi>Divinity,</hi> knowingly created at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> courſe complement to him at his Creation, after he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended one of them. <hi>Hujus te Theologiae creo Doctorem,</hi> meaning the <hi>Arminian Divinity,</hi> whence ever after to his Death, poſſibly, he took the liberty to <hi>Profeſs</hi> it as the <hi>Doctrine of our Church;</hi> yea, and they muſt be <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> too,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33146:19"/>though not <hi>from,</hi> yet in the National Church, and that's the worſt ſort of Schiſme, becauſe that which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture chiefly, if not only, taketh notice of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe who will ſing <hi>no Pſalms,</hi> muſt be Schiſmaticks too; for ſurely, that's an <hi>act of Worſhip</hi> in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and owned by her; yea, and thoſe that do not ordinarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to all <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>Formes</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy, do they approve of them?</hi> The worſe, they ſtill (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this deſcription) make a <hi>Shiſme</hi> in the Church. <hi>Quaery:</hi> Whether none of the Conformiſts do this? I could tell him of ſome, nay One (and he no mean One neither) that openly told the People, <hi>ſinging of Pſalms</hi> was one of the <hi>Idols of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; there were three <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>keeping the Sabbath</hi> were the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>§. 40. Now if the <hi>Author</hi> could have been content to have deſcribed the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England, the number of <hi>profeſſed Chriſtians in it united in the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33146:19"/>ſame Doctrines neceſſary to Salvation, and in the ſame Acts of Worſhip;</hi> the Definition had been ſhorter, many of theſe had been included, and we had all been agreed. But to be ſure to make all the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> Shiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, he firſt <hi>Deſcribes</hi> a thing <hi>not in being,</hi> and which never was ſince Chriſt came, and then deſcribes it in ſuch a manner as if he could create it, would do very many of his own friends far more hurt than us.</p>
            <p>§. 41. In the mean time, we muſt freely yeild him ſuch a <hi>National Church</hi> as we before deſcribed, and the <hi>King</hi> the <hi>Supreme Head</hi> of it, not in a capacity to Preach or adminiſter the Sacrament, or exerciſe any act in it ſtrictly an Eccleſiaſtical by Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, but to <hi>Protect it,</hi> to <hi>enjoyn</hi> the <hi>fulfilling in it what God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded;</hi> to do as much (in it) in ſhort, as any <hi>King of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah (as a King) might do, and to make rules and conſtitutions about it. But we deny that our Meetings are any more <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> in, or from this Church,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33146:20"/>then the Meeting of Chriſtians to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the ſame acts of worſhip, is a <hi>Schiſme</hi> from that part of this Church, which meet for that end in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 42. Nor is he helped at all by ſaying <hi>Our Churches are not of the ſame conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine of Schiſme, <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> which he ſays was Mr. <hi>Cawdrys</hi> anſwer to Dr. <hi>Owen;</hi> let Mr. <hi>Cawdry,</hi> or who will ſay ſo, <hi>Dolus verſatur in Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> What is the difference, did Chriſt conſtitute theirs? We truſt he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted ours, that is, by the Rules gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his Word. Were theirs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by <hi>Parliament?</hi> (that will be hard to prove as to the firſt conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Pariſhes</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were firſt made by a <hi>Popiſh Arch-Biſhop,</hi> the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment afterwards, or Cuſtom rather might confirm them). Doth it then make a <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> to depart to a Church not eſtabliſhed by humane Law or Cuſtom? How elſe are we of another conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Is not the ſame Doctrine Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſame Sacraments adminiſtred?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33146:20"/>the ſame <hi>acts of Worſhip</hi> performed? Where's the difference? <hi>In the Modes, Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> only; And theſe all of humane inſtitution. This is that which the Church of God never before called <hi>Schiſme,</hi> &amp; which the Apoſtles ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought of. Do not we agree in the ſame <hi>Government?</hi> That concerns us not yet, while we are clearing our ſelves only from a Church, which the Author muſt ſhew us capable of any ſuch <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> as Chriſt hath appointed <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal</hi> to his Church. In the mean time, as to the <hi>National Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, we deny that we are guilty of any <hi>Schiſme,</hi> either <hi>in it,</hi> or <hi>from it;</hi> ſo that the whole charge muſt reſt upon <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches,</hi> and our (pretended) ſeparation from them.</p>
            <p>§. 43. This is that other <hi>Church-ſtate</hi> mentioned by Mr. <hi>Caudry,</hi> and quoted by our Author, <hi>ch.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 57. theſe he calls <hi>Parochial Congregations:</hi> We are (he ſaith) <hi>guilty of Schiſme from them;</hi> we all agree that theſe are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the name of Churches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>As they are leſſer parts of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33146:21"/>Church,</hi> and ſo capable of the name of the whole; thus we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed united to them, as we were united to the Catholick Church, and united ſtill to them as unto that; owning the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, his Word and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and profeſſing a ſubjection to them: But this is not the <hi>other ſtate</hi> he ſpeaks of, by which he can mean nothing but a <hi>governing ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly therefore; Theſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Societies</hi> may be conſidered as perfectly, or more <hi>imperfectly Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized,</hi> furniſhed with all <hi>Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> requiſite <hi>and walking in Goſpel or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> or <hi>not ſo furniſhed,</hi> or ſo walking. The <hi>Author</hi> tells his Reader in a latter Book, called <hi>Advice to the Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts:</hi> That the ſum of what the Author of the <hi>ſhort Reflections</hi> offered, lay in two things; the latter of which he delivered thus. <q>
                  <hi>Our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Churches are no true Churches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Advice to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 72.</note> 
                  <hi>or at leſt they are ſo faulty as they may be lawfully ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33146:21"/>
            <p>We have read over the Book; and good <hi>Reader,</hi> at thy leiſure, do but read over that Pamplet, the ſecond <hi>chapt.</hi> particularly the 13, 14, 15. <hi>pages,</hi> and ſee whether this Author hath, or no, dealt ingeniouſly with him, <hi>p.</hi> 14. He ſpeaks of theſe Societies, <q>
                  <hi>as parts of the Catholick Churches,</hi> and ſaith,<note place="margin">Short Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>In this Notion we cannot deny that every Pariſh, yea, Family of Chriſtians, is a true Church:</hi>
               </q> But he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed concludes, that out of ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches, it muſt be lawful to <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Church,</hi> for all particular Churches in the world, are gathered out of the <hi>Catholick Viſible Church;</hi> even <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> when converted, muſt be of the <hi>Catholick Viſible Church,</hi> before they can form a particular Church: In this ſtate, and no other, muſt all Parochial Societies be that have no Miniſter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we will have <hi>Organical Governing Churches</hi> without any <hi>Governours,</hi> which we think is a contradiction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 15. He takes notice of another Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, as <hi>Miniſterial,</hi> by <hi>which</hi> (he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33146:22"/>ſaith) <hi>he underſt ands a competent number of Chriſtians, who have either firſt choſen, or after ſubmitted to</hi> A. B. <hi>as their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> he might indeed have ſpared this Notion; I do not remember I have met with it in any Author, but Mr. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford;</hi> and the truth is, if it be a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Miniſter,</hi> I do not underſtand how he Preacheth otherwiſe to them, than as he is (ſo far) an Officer of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi> and they a part of that vaſt body. He conſiders theſe people</p>
            <p>
               <q>Either as living in the uſe of all Goſpel-Ordinances, or as at preſent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving without ſome Ordinances, or having them ſo unduly adminiſtred, as may offer juſt cauſe of doubt to ſome Chriſtians, whether they may lawfully communicate with them or no:—He adds, we do believe that from ſuch a Church as is furniſhed with a duely ſent, able, painful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, regularly adminiſtring the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt, ſo as people may communicate with them without ſin, and preſſing forward to that perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in order, which in all things they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33146:22"/>have not attained Chriſtians as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore united to them, may not ſeparate without ſin.</q> He did not indeed ſay, but I dare ſay for him, he believed there were many ſuch Parochial Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>England,</hi> and he hints it, when he ſaith, <q>This was that indeed which ſome <hi>Presbyterians</hi> reflected upon our Brethren of the Congregational per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, and theſe were thoſe Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Churches which they contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for as true Churches.</q> Was this to ſay Parochial Societies were no true Churches? Reader, judge in his 15. <hi>page,</hi> He tells us; <q>There is yet a more perfect Notion of a particular Church as perfectly Organical, and furniſhed with all its affairs, and walking in all points of Goſpel Order.—He adds, ſuch particular Churches were in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Parochial Societies in <hi>England;</hi> and there is no doubt but ſuch <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Churches</hi> were <hi>True Churches,</hi> from which cauſeleſs, and unneceſſary ſeparation is ſinful. Indeed, he ſays, How far other Parochial Churches were true Churches, avowed ſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33146:23"/>by Presbyterians, he was yet to learn.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And his Anſwer is, for any thing I ſee in his <hi>Remarques,</hi> yet to teach him, and I believe will ſo continue. For his gueſſes at what the Author meant by <hi>Perfection of Order.</hi> He I am ſure will tell him he means no more, <q>Than a capacity to adminiſter all the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt proper to a particular Church.</q> The <hi>Word, Sacraments, and Cenſures</hi> of Jundical <hi>Admonition, Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion,</hi> and <hi>Excommunication,</hi> which they cannot do till they have <hi>Officers.</hi> I believe it muſt be a caſe of Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſity muſt juſtifie a ſingle Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in <hi>Suſpending,</hi> or <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> but that thoſe that help him muſt needs be perſons not ordained to the Miniſtry. I do not think he believes, but that there may be more Miniſters (if the Parochial Society hath more than one) or others choſen by that Church. And if any will contend that the body of the people muſt joyn with him in thoſe acts (though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves his private judgment in the caſe)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33146:23"/>yet he will not contend eſpecially as to <hi>Excommunication,</hi> becauſe he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not to what purpoſe Officers ſhould caſt any out of the fellowſhip of their Church, who are yet reſolved to have fellowſhip with him: He thinks he hath read ſome rule of the ancient Church, that <hi>none ought</hi> to be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated <hi>ſine plebis conſenſu,</hi> without the conſent of the body of the Church. But was this to ſay, <hi>Our Parochial Churches</hi> are no true Churches?</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Author ſaid <hi>they were all true parts of the Catholick Churches, and ſo true Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author believes <hi>There are many Parochial Societies</hi> that are true Churches in the ſecond ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He plainly ſays there were many ſo in the third and moſt perfect ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What pittiful diſingenuity was this in this Writer of the <hi>Doctrine of Schiſme,</hi> thus to repreſent his Adverſary? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed from the Authors diſcourſe it plainly appears, That he did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33146:24"/>
            <p n="1">1. That Pariſhes that had no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Miniſter, or faithful Miniſter, were true <hi>Organical Churches;</hi> but only true parts of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church he grants them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no <hi>Parochial Societies</hi> as ſuch, were true Organical Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though ſome Pariſhes had able and painful Miniſters, yet if they never choſe them as their Paſtors, nor ſubmitted to them as ſuch, They were not true <hi>Organical Churches;</hi> or thoſe who had not ſo ſubmitted, were not true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ever united to them.</p>
            <p>§. 44. 4. <q>That if perſons living in thoſe Societies, had choſen and ſubmitted to a Miniſter as their Paſtor, believing him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and faithful, and profeſſing to preſs after a perfection in order, &amp; they afterwards found the contrary, that he proved negligent in his work, leud in his Life, corrupt in his Doctrine, unfaithful in his Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33146:24"/>and there were no viſible hope of a Reformation, that in this caſe they might peaceably and charitably with-draw from that communion, and joyn with a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</q> Theſe ſeem to be that Authors principles, which amount to this, that all <hi>Parochial Societies,</hi> either <hi>are no true Governing Churches,</hi> or the <hi>parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned were never united to them;</hi> or if they were <hi>once united to them,</hi> yet their ſeceſſion from them was <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,</hi> and therefore could not be <hi>a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſeparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 45. Now what ſays the Author to this? Will <hi>he ſay that Parochial So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties</hi> are all, <hi>True Governing Churches.</hi> Surely he will not ſay ſo, if he own <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy;</hi> for men of that perſuaſion muſt maintain <hi>That the Biſhop</hi> is the ſole <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the Dioceſs;</hi> that Government belongs only to him, that <hi>Pariſh-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> are but his <hi>Curates,</hi> according to this Model; ſurely every Parochial Society is not a Governing Church; do they ſay ſo? we ſay ſo too. So we are agreed, and not chargeable with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33146:25"/>gathering Churches out of true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Will he ſay that Parochial So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties having <hi>no peculiar Paſtor,</hi> or <hi>none that reſides with his Flock,</hi> are <hi>true Miniſterial Churches.</hi> Surely this in the firſt part is a contradiction, to talk of a <hi>Miniſterial Church without a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> And the ſecond part, contrary to our Authors judgment (if conſiſtent to it ſelf,) for if the <hi>cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Members</hi> be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,<note place="margin">Doctrine of Schiſm, <hi>p. 85.</hi>
               </note> and that as he tells us, <hi>by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and ſo <hi>Divine,</hi> the <hi>cohabitation of the head with thoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, muſt</hi> be neceſſary too by the ſame Law.</p>
            <p>§. 46. No, but he will ſay, They were <hi>united to them,</hi> thoſe of them that were <hi>true Miniſterial Churches:</hi> And 2. <hi>Being united, they have no juſt and neceſſary cauſe of ſeparation.</hi> Theſe are the two things to be tried; for the tryal of this iſſue we muſt enquire.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is a ſufficient Union of a perſon to a true Miniſterial Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author ſeems not to think
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33146:25"/>meer <hi>cohabitation</hi> doth it, though he thinks it of the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> (which I do not underſtand) that the Members of a Church ſhould <hi>coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate.</hi> I think it very expedient and neceſſary that they ſhould live ſo near together, that ordinarily they may meet for worſhip together in one place, and be able mutually to perform the dutys of exhortation and admonition one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; yet the Author will not ſay this makes their <hi>Union</hi> in <hi>a Church Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganical;</hi> beſides many queſtions would ariſe, as <hi>How near they muſt live? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none may live betwixt them?</hi> What if a <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> or <hi>Pagan hires an Houſe betwixt them,</hi> &amp;c? What the Author doth ſay, I will candidly transſcribe, as I find it in his <hi>Doctrine of Schiſme,</hi> ch. 13. <hi>p.</hi> 89. <q>
                  <hi>They were Baptized unto theſe particular Churches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doctrine of Schiſm. <hi>chap.</hi> 13.89.</note> 
                  <hi>as well as into the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and the known Laws both of Church and State, oblige their Conſciences to communion with them, —Their ordinary attending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33146:26"/>the publick Worſhip as they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally do, or have done, concludes them by their own conſent,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here now are three things brought to prove the Union,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Baptiſme,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Laws of men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Their <hi>own conſent</hi> implicitely, by their ordinary <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Worſhip</hi> in <hi>Parochial Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Let us candidly examine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any of theſe will do it.</p>
            <p>§. 47. That men are Baptized <hi>into a particular Church,</hi> and <hi>by it made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Members of it,</hi> is what I cannot yeeld. <hi>Baptiſme</hi> indeed admitts into the <hi>Univerſal Church.</hi> If any <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Brethren have judged more, I muſt underſtand their Reaſons before I ſubſcribe their Opinions; beſides that, hardly one of twenty Chriſtians were Baptized in that Parochial Society wherein they live; when at years of diſcretion, Baptiſme indeed gives a Chriſtian a claim to a Memberſhip in ſome particular Church, but makes no Union with it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the ſecond, it can have no truth in it, till he hath proved <hi>That it is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33146:26"/>the will of Chriſt, that Chriſtians ſhould be Members of that particular Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized Church, where their Superiours in Church or State will command.</hi> As this is no civil thing, but Spiritual, and ſuch wherein the Souls of Chriſtians, as to their Eternal concerns, are highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. So neither is it a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; but let the Author prove what I ſay he muſt prove in this caſe, and we will ſay more. We think, though God hath expreſly no where told Chriſtians in his Word (which had been almoſt impoſſible) what particular Church they ſhould be of; yet he hath obliged them to attend what in their Conſciences they judg, and upon experience they find the moſt propable and effectual means for their <hi>Inſtruction, Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Salvation;</hi> not expecting he ſhould work miracles for them. God hath no where told every Man, what Woman he ſhould Marry; yet ſurely he hath not left Magiſtrates a power to determine all their Subjects to Wives. Yet we think this concern of Souls
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33146:27"/>is much higher, and that there is as much difference in <hi>Miniſters</hi> as in <hi>Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The laſt therefore is all, for which there can be any pretence, <hi>conſent</hi> indeed will do it. And we will grant, that this conſent may be either <hi>Explicit</hi> or <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit. Explicit</hi> when Chriſtians have either <hi>firſt choſen,</hi> or upon recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>accepted</hi> a truly ſent, able, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter to be their Paſtor, to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Ordinances of God to them: Or more <hi>Implicit,</hi> when though they have not firſt called him, nor ſo expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly declared their conſent to him; yet they have <hi>ordinarily and ſtatedly walked with him in the fellowſhip of all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> But here muſt be conſidered</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is a great deal of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt deſiring, conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to, and accepting of one as a Miniſter of the Goſpel to Preach to the Parochial Society, where a Chriſtan lives, as it is a part of the Catholick Church; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to ſuch a one to be <hi>his or
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33146:27"/>their Paſtor,</hi> in order to a <hi>Church Organical,</hi> It muſt be a conſent of the latter Nature. I may conſent and deſire one to Preach to the people in the precinct where I live, and yet have no thoughts of conſenting to him as my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there is a great deal of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt <hi>an occaſional hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and it may be <hi>receiving the Sacrament</hi> with a Miniſter, and a <hi>ſlated ordinary</hi> fixed <hi>doing of it.</hi> If a Chriſtian, that is of a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church at <hi>London,</hi> goeth down to <hi>York,</hi> and be to ſtay there 6 or 9 moneths, and ordinarily hears and receives the Sacrament there, while he is there; this will indeed prove his owning the Church of <hi>York</hi> as a true Church, &amp; having communion with it, but not that he is a Member of it. Suppoſe many Chriſtians, who were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſtated Members of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but for 10 or 12 years laſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33146:28"/>paſt, have not been able to walk with their Paſtors and Brethren in all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, meeting in the ſame place to worſhip God, have in the time ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, or often heard a <hi>Parochial Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> nay, ſometimes received the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi> This indeed proves their Charity, that they lookt upon that <hi>Society as a true Church;</hi> but it doth not prove them Members of it, nor their conſent to ſuch a Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; no, not to ſuch a Miniſter as their Paſtor, though it may be, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him for the good of the place where they lived, as a Preacher of the Goſpel to them. If indeed they were of no other ſtated particular Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and did ordinarily joyn in <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Communion</hi> with ſuch a Miniſter, it goes far to prove an <hi>Union</hi> by <hi>implicit conſent,</hi> and we think ſuch cannot plead, <hi>They were not United.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 48. It is true, theſe Notions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout particular <hi>Churches,</hi> Worſhip and <hi>Government,</hi> eſpecially the firſt and laſt, were very dark, and little under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by many good men, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1641.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33146:28"/>and no wonder if it be conſidered.
<list>
                  <item>1. How <hi>very few Books were then wrote of them,</hi> on <hi>the Presbyterian ſide.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. And how poenal it was made to <hi>have,</hi> or <hi>read them,</hi> and how little hope before that time appeared of reducing any thing had been ſaid to practice.</item>
               </list>
Some of our <hi>Congregational Brethren</hi> having had more reſt and freedom, and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of exerciſe in N. <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were better ſtudied in them. As alſo our <hi>Brethren of</hi> Scotland. This for a few years occaſioned great animoſities. Yet I could never read, nor hear quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that even then any judicious <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> ever granted:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That all Parochial Societies</hi> were true Organized <hi>Churches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Nor that living in a Pariſh did more than give the Chriſtian a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to claim admiſſion into that Society.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome few years paſſing, and mens heats abating, and peaceable converſe each with other, better advantaging them to underſtand one another, than at firſt they did, they began to be far
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33146:29"/>more clear and unanimous in their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and more charitable in their practices.</p>
            <p>§. 40. I cannot ſpeak for all, but I can ſpeak for a very competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſo many (as in one County) would be perſwaded to meet in 1657. &amp; 58. They agreed in the following <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a perſon fit for Church-fellowſhip in all Ordinances and Priviledges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I have by me, alſo the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures affixed to prove this.</note>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>One that is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome competent knowledge in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Whoſe life &amp; conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is free from all groſs and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous evils, both of Omiſſion and Commiſſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Who maketh ſuch a profeſſion of Faith and Holineſs as may give unto the Church a probable hope in the judgment of true Chriſtian Charity, that there are ſome ſeeds of ſome ſpiritual work of God in his ſoul.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Who profeſſeth a willing ſubjection to the Goſpel, and all the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo giveth up himſelf to the Lord, and his Church, to walk in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33146:29"/>all duties of Obedience and Love, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
To which they added, and then ſubſcribed.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>We acknowledge ſuch Churches to be true Churches, as conſiſt of ſuch perſons coming together as are here deſcribed, and ſuch to be true Miniſters as are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by, and unto ſuch a people.</hi> And we <hi>further acknowledge ſuch to be Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and their Miniſters to be true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, though ſome bad with the good agreed to the call of thoſe Miniſters, or to own and embrace them; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there were ſome diſorder, and failing in the Ordination, and coming in of ſuch Miniſters.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By this, theſe <hi>Presbyterians</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments eaſily appeared, what <hi>Parochial Societies</hi> they judged, <hi>True Churches;</hi> and alſo what they judged neceſſary to make up the <hi>Union of a Member</hi> with a <hi>particular</hi> Organical Church.</p>
            <p>§. 50. I think I can from a Friend alſo, aſſure the Author that the perſon whom this <hi>Author</hi> doth ſomewhere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare not only a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> but one of great <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> (as indeed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33146:30"/>he was) I mean Mr. <hi>Brinſley</hi> of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> was the man drew up this Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, recommended it to his Brethen; himſelf agreed in it, and they alſo, and made it a great foundation for an <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> betwixt them and their <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Brethren.</hi> For my own part, I am much of his mind: We ſay many of the Miniſters and people he reflects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> neither were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thus united to <hi>Parochial Societies,</hi> nor we in capacity ſo to be, becauſe formally <hi>Paſters and Members</hi> elſe-where.</p>
            <p>§. 51. But the Author thinks the Law <hi>forbidding Miniſters to Preach in the Parochial Temples,</hi> hath <hi>diſſolved this Relation.</hi> In this we differ from him, and deſire a better proof of it, both <hi>de facto,</hi> then he hath given us, and <hi>de jure,</hi> Then <hi>Solomons</hi> putting <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biathur</hi> from the Prieſts Office, who <hi>had deſerved to dye</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells him firſt;) but more of that by and by. I do not profeſs ſtrictly to Anſwer the Authors Book about <hi>Schiſme:</hi> It is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt an <hi>Author</hi> able enough
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33146:30"/>to ſpeak for himſelf; but ſomething I muſt ſay to this and ſome other paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, only as they come athwart me in maintaining the Negative part of my <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and juſtifying my ſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the clamour of <hi>Schiſme.</hi> Therefore in <hi>Doctrine of Schiſme,</hi> p. 75. I find theſe words,</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>What if a man hath a mind to be Friends with him,</hi> (that we deſire, for we are for peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>and ſhould grant that thoſe Miniſters were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded</hi> [diſcommiſſioned he ſhould have ſaid, or unordained as to] <hi>their Miniſtry within the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and that thoſe Churches were not diſſolved by having new Paſtors,</hi> [he forgets the Biſhop, Curates he ſhould have ſaid] <hi>no more then the Kingdom, when the King dyes; and yet certainly the King and People are as much conſtitutive parts of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as Paſtor and People of a Church; who will ſay, that conſiders what he ſaith, that a particular Church is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by the death or removal of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33146:31"/>Paſtor.</hi>
               </q> Afterward he tell us the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Dr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> then of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as to the <hi>removing of</hi> Abiather; and laſtly, <hi>p.</hi> 77. <q>
                  <hi>That he hath thought hitherto, that the diſtinction of the Office, and of the exerciſe of the Office had gone uncontrouled amongſt</hi> Presbyterians; <hi>and though the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt depend not (not upon the Chriſtian Magiſtrate for their Office) and he cannot degrade them, yet</hi> quoad Exercitium, <hi>as to the Exerciſe of it in his Dominions he might, and that he had power to ſilence ſuch as are judged unmeet to Preach;</hi> and in this Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> confirms him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 52. He will at leaſt <hi>(ex abundanti)</hi> grant that man hath no power to ſay to thoſe, <hi>Do not preach,</hi> to whom Chriſt and his Church hath ſaid, <hi>Go and Preach;</hi> it is ſome relief yet, that he will in any thing ſuffer us to acknowledge <hi>Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem coeli.</hi> The Miniſters were not put out of <hi>Office,</hi> 1662. then; Onely forbidden to <hi>exerciſe that Office within</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of</hi> England; but where was this prohibition? The Law only
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33146:31"/>ſaith, <hi>in publick Churches and Chappels.</hi> But the Churches he ſaith were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved any more by <hi>having new Paſtors, than the Kingdom is diſſolved when the King dyes</hi> [he ſhould have ſaid by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a new King.] The Queſtion is, whether the Churches were not diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the <hi>removal of their Paſtor.</hi> We think not: ſo he ſaith, Are we not agreed? the <hi>Governours</hi> were in being; the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned</hi> in being; only the <hi>Governours</hi> were in Priſon, and for a time could not exerciſe their Office in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. But if the Governours were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commiſſioned, unordained, ſurely the <hi>Governing Church</hi> was diſſolved as the <hi>Governing Kingdom;</hi> (ſo far as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours act by commiſſion) is by his leave diſſolved at the death of a King, as we all know.</p>
            <p>§. 53. He asks who will ſay <hi>That a particular Church is diſſolved upon the Death or Removal of the Faſtor.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer any one that underſtands ſenſe, if there were no other Governour, and he be not in being, ſurely the <hi>particular organical Governing Church is diſſolved,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:33146:32"/>the body is not neceſſitated to part, but at liberty, whether they will agree to the next <hi>Paſtor,</hi> yea or no; his Friend Mr. <hi>Candry</hi> hath ſaid ſo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> had ſaid, <q>
                  <hi>If the Church be not a Church without Officers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cawdrys</hi> Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> Survey, <hi>chap.</hi> 8. <hi>page</hi> 133.</note> 
                  <hi>then as oft as the Officers dye, the Church dyeth alſo.</hi>
               </q> That is an <hi>Authoritative Governing Church;</hi> and indeed, for any to ſay <hi>a Church</hi> is a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial</hi> Church, without a Miniſter, or a <hi>Governing</hi> Church <hi>without a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> is a piece of ſence I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p>§. 54. But to return to the Caſe of <hi>Abiathar,</hi> which is brought to prove the power of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> to put Miniſters as well out of their Office, as out of their <hi>Preferments, Poſſeſſions,</hi> and <hi>publick Temples</hi> (all which is granted and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Queſtion.) I have nothing to do with any mans Opinion in the caſe. Let us fairly debate and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the caſe, and ſee whether it will conclude for the Author, yea or no.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33146:32"/>
               <hi>Aaron</hi> was Gods undoubted High-Prieſt, immediately conſtituted ſo by himſelf. His Sons were alſo ordained by God to ſucceed him. <hi>Aaron</hi> had four Sons, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Nanab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> (theſe <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. dyed before their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>Eleazar</hi> and <hi>Ithamor.</hi> By Gods ſpecial order <hi>Eleazar</hi> was made the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> inſtead of <hi>Aaron,</hi> Numb. 20.26, 28. <hi>Eleazer</hi> died, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.33. <hi>Phinehas</hi> his Son ſucceeded him, <hi>Jud.</hi> 20.28. Here the Scripture leaveth us. The next High Prieſt we read of, was <hi>Eli,</hi> for his neglect to correct his <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Sons,</hi> God threatneth that he would cut off his Poſterity <hi>from his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.33, 35. and raiſe up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf a ſaithful <hi>Prieſt:</hi> This was the known will of God, declared to <hi>Eli</hi> by two Prophets; his Sons <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> died before him. <hi>Ahilub</hi> is by Divines concluded to have ſucceeded him; he is called <hi>Ichabods Bother,</hi> 1 Sam. 14.3. That is <hi>Elies</hi> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child. <hi>Ahiah</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Ahilub,</hi> as is plain from 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Ahimelech</hi> ſucceeded him, as is plain, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.11.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33146:33"/>Here God's Vengeance on <hi>Elies</hi> Family began to appear. <hi>Saul ſlays</hi> him and all his Fathers Houſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.16. only <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>Abiathar</hi> eſcapeth and fleeth unto <hi>David,</hi> and was with him in all his troubles by <hi>Saul;</hi> but in the mean time it would be enquired who was <hi>High Prieſt</hi> for <hi>Saul</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> and this the Scripture ſaith not, (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he little regarded the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Order</hi> inſtituted by God.) But it is a greater difficulty how the <hi>H. Prieſthood</hi> came out of the line of <hi>Eleazer, Aarons</hi> Eldeſt Son, into the line of <hi>Ithamar</hi> the Younger Son of <hi>Aaron?</hi> Nor doth the Scripture reſolve us, nor <hi>Joſephus,</hi> who aſſureth us, <hi>Eli</hi> was of the Family of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamar,</hi> and the firſt of it, but ſays on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>He took the Prieſthood,</hi> of whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily <hi>Abiathar</hi> was the laſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſephus,</hi> v. 62.12.</note> This <hi>Abiathar</hi> was one of thoſe, who during <hi>Davids</hi> life, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his <hi>Will,</hi> proclaimed <hi>Adonijah</hi> King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.25. which was no leſs than <hi>High Treaſon. Solomon</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to account for it, <hi>ſpares his life</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:33146:33"/>for the kindneſs he had ſhewed to his Father, telling him he was <hi>worthy of death,</hi> but confineth him to <hi>Anathoth,</hi> (where he could not execute the Prieſts Office) 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.26, 27. So ſaith the Text, <hi>He thruſt out</hi> Abiathar <hi>from being Prieſt unto the Lord;</hi> and it is added, <hi>That he might fulfil the Word of the Lord, which he ſpake concerning the Houſe of</hi> Eli <hi>in</hi> Shiloh: yet 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.3. In the rool of the Officers we find <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi> and <hi>Abiathar were the Prieſts;</hi> ſo that it ſeems he was a Prieſt ſtill, What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is to be underſtood by, <hi>He put him out of the Prieſts Office:</hi> 'tis certain, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.35. he made <hi>Zadoc</hi> in his room, who was of the Sons of <hi>Eleazar,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.3. We cannot underſtand from Scripture, but that the <hi>High-Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> ought to have been in the Family of <hi>Eleazer;</hi> and it is like the diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly times of the Judges altered it. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> reſtoreth it, and in doing it, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled what he knew was the will of God about <hi>Elies</hi> Family. It is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable but <hi>David</hi> had done it before, but for <hi>Abiathars</hi> peculiar Service to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33146:34"/>him in his troubles. Now we have the caſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Solomon</hi> knew that <hi>Abiathar</hi> was of the younger Houſe from <hi>Aaron,</hi> whereas the High-Prieſthood truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to the Elder.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He knew alſo God had declared his Will to root out the Houſe of <hi>Eli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This <hi>Abiathar</hi> had committed the higheſt crime; <hi>Solomon</hi> might have put him to death, but for his kindneſs to his Father as to life he ſpares him, but thinks fit to ſend him far enough from the Court, and the place where the High-Prieſts Office was to be Executed at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and to confine him to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathoth,</hi> where he could not execute the Office of the High-Prieſt; and ſo he was in effect turned from the <hi>High-Prieſts Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And <hi>Zadoc,</hi> to whom that Office was due, is inveſted with it: But <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athar</hi> remains a <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſtill, &amp; is ſo called after, and joyned next to <hi>Zadoc;</hi> but the <hi>High Prieſthood</hi> could not truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him, but to the Elder Houſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33146:34"/>from <hi>Aaron;</hi> and beſides, God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his Will, that this ſhould be done; he is <hi>ſaid to have done it,</hi> that <hi>he might fulfil the Word of the Lord,</hi> and he that did it was a man inſpired by God, and a <hi>Pen-man of Holy Writ.</hi> What will follow from hence think we? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>chiefeſt Prieſts</hi> from their <hi>Preferments, Dignities,</hi> and their <hi>own Courts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That in caſe they have <hi>deſerved death,</hi> and <hi>the Magiſtrate thinks fit to ſhew mercy,</hi> but <hi>yet to puniſh them with Baniſhment to remote places</hi> where their flock cannot come; he may thus in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect turn them out from their <hi>Paſtoral Relation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That in caſe he finds them <hi>no true Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> he may <hi>forbid them to Miniſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That if God from Heaven by a revelation, or by any plain Scripture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to turn true Miniſters out of Office, they may do it.</hi> I can ſee nothing more, let the Author make his beſt of this.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:33146:35"/>
            <p>§. 55. But he had thought the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the Office,</hi> and <hi>the exerciſe of it, had been uncontrouled by the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; and that they had granted, that though the Magiſtrate could not degrade them, yet as to the exerciſe of their Office he might, and that he had power to ſilence ſuch as he judged unmeet to Preach. Presbyterians</hi> can (without the help of this Authors Logick) diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Office and the exerciſe of the Office,</hi> and make one diſtinction more between the <hi>exerciſe of the Office</hi> in <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick places,</hi> (undoubtedly in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates diſpoſal,) and in their own <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſes,</hi> or in the private Houſes of others. They do believe it in the power of the Magiſtrate, though not to take away their <hi>Office,</hi> or <hi>Relation to their Flock.</hi> Yet to hinder the <hi>exerciſe of it,</hi> and that they ought to obey him, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to forbear the exerciſe of it in <hi>publick places</hi> belonging to the Magiſtrates; and accordingly have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally been ſo obedient, though the Law ſo far, be not ſo plain, that any are <hi>prohibited to Preach, except ſuch as are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33146:35"/>diſabled,</hi> which is the caſe of very few. They know <hi>Paul</hi> Preached in his hired Houſe at <hi>Rome,</hi> Act. 28. and in the School of <hi>Tirannus,</hi> when the Jewiſh Rulers forbad them the Synagogues; the Office not taken away, nor to be taken away, they conclude the Relation atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Office abiding. But hitherto we have only juſtified our firſt Plea. <hi>It is no ſeparation, becauſe there never was an Union, nor could be of very many of us to a Parochial Miniſterial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church.</hi> And conſidering it only as a part of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> we are in all points one with it.</p>
            <p>§. 56. But we will ſuppoſe that this is not the caſe of all our Brethren; but <hi>ſome have been United to the Parochial Societies,</hi> wherein they lived, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly conſented to be one body with them, by not only hearing the Miniſters there, but receiving <hi>the Communion with them.</hi> What ſhall be ſaid for them? <hi>We ſay they are not ſinfully ſeparated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Are they ſeparated?</hi> They now indeed meet for worſhip in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that ſtatedly; but <hi>do they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33146:36"/>the Miniſters or Churches,</hi> from which they are come? do they not own them as <hi>true Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>ſuch Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as true Churches?</hi> Do they not pay to the Miniſters, &amp; love the Brethren? where's the <hi>Schiſme</hi> then? For when men have ſaid all they can, <hi>Schiſme</hi> is a ſin againſt the <hi>command of Love to our Neighbour.</hi> It is no command of God, you ſhall be of this Congregation or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, other then it falls under general precepts, commanding us to uſe the beſt means for our Souls. Now can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I love my Neighbour, except I dwell in his Family, or chuſe her for my Wife, or him for my Husband: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is moſt certain, I am bound to love my own <hi>Soul</hi> in the firſt place; and as an Evidence to that, I am tied to uſe the beſt means I can (not contradicted by God's Word) according to my own Conſcience (which certainly muſt judg for me in my higheſt concern) for the Salvation of it.</p>
            <p>§. 57. I am a-ware of what this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath ſaid, <hi>That a man may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from a Congregation to which he was
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33146:36"/>United, either to enjoy the Ordinances of God more powerfully, or purely, or perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred in another, convenient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me to joyn with.</hi> This is the ſubſtance of what he hath ſaid and quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from others as their Opinion. But this will never enter into my thoughts. Let them ſpeak plainly to this. <hi>Is it not the duty of every Chriſtian to uſe what appears to his Conſcience the beſt and moſt probable means for his Salvation?</hi> The light of Nature as well as Scripture will evince this. Now I would fain know of any perſon what it is under Heaven, (except the bare Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) that God hath appointed as means for the <hi>Inſtruction, Edification,</hi> and <hi>Salvation of my Soul,</hi> but <hi>the gifts of his Miniſters</hi> or People, (with which, in order to theſe ends) his holy Spirit works not miraculouſly, but in a natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal orderly way <hi>ſecundum quae nactus eſt, Organa.</hi> There is nothing more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident than that in Miniſters, there is a great diverſity of Gifts, and as much a diverſity of <hi>Wills, Humours,</hi> and <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;</hi> and alſo a great variety of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33146:37"/>
               <hi>Capacities.</hi> There's nothing more evident than that our Miniſters <hi>parts, method</hi> of <hi>Preaching,</hi> &amp;c. is really more fitted to the <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and <hi>Edification</hi> of ſome people, than the <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> of others are; as we ſay every <hi>good Man makes not a good Husband for every good Woman;</hi> ſo it is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly true, that every able and good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is not a fit and good Inſtructor for every good Chriſtian; they poſſibly underſtand not his <hi>language,</hi> nor cannot <hi>learn his method</hi> (poſſibly 'tis <hi>Cryptick,</hi> and requires a Schollar to underſtand it. Shall theſe people be perpetually ſtaked down in the caſe, that let their Souls be never ſo much concerned, they muſt not ordinarily joyn with <hi>another Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and hear him, though their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be convenient enough for it? or muſt theſe perſons (poſſibly to the loſs of their Trade and Livelihood, which in Towns lyes much upon their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) be forced to remove into that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pariſh; where hath God required any ſuch thing?</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33146:37"/>
            <p>§. 58. Beſides that, I underſtand not much thoſe of my Brethren that are ſo Zealous in this point. In my little dealings in the World, I uſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be afraid of that <hi>Trades-man,</hi> whom I perceive uſing arts to tye me to his Shop; and upon that <hi>Work-man</hi> that I ſee endeavouring to oblige me to none but himſelf. I fear always, they have no good meaning toward me; and I ſhould fear my ſelf, that I meant not to deal well with Souls if I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſtake them to my Miniſtry. I ſhould ſuſpect my ſelf of <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Self-intereſt,</hi> or ſome other <hi>ſcurvy Luſt or Paſſion.</hi> If I think none ſo able as my ſelf, 'tis <hi>Pride;</hi> if I would have them to fill my Congregation, it is <hi>Self-intereſt.</hi> If I would <hi>ſave their Souls,</hi> ſo may ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and poſſibly be a better inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it, at leaſt he is more likely, if <hi>ſound in the Faith, able, and painful,</hi> becauſe they have a more fancy to him. In ſhort, I have for ſome good time been an unworthy Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el; I thank God, I can ſay, that as I never denyed any Chriſtian deſirous to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33146:38"/>leave me, my Licenſe to do it; ſo I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had an ill thought of any that did it; but ſaid with my ſelf, The fewer Souls I have will be under my charge, the leſſer my account will be: And that which much confirm'd me in this, was my reading <hi>Chryſoſtom's</hi> expreſſing a fear that but a <hi>few Miniſters would be ſaved,</hi> becauſe their work and charge was ſo great; which if well conſidered, would abate our trouble for the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Auditory, and rather make us rejoyce. I have a number not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable under my charge now, and I can ſay, I dearly love them; and ſhould think I did not, if I ſhould not declare my free leave for them to leave my Miniſtry, and joyn with any other of ſound faith and holy life, under whom they ſhould think they could profit more than by me; and I do think this the duty of every Miniſter. I do not think this is any ſinful ſeparation which <hi>Schiſme</hi> doth import.</p>
            <p>§. 59. But laſtly: Suppoſing ſuch a departing from a Church, to which we are united, be to be called <hi>Separation;</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33146:38"/>yet it is not ſinful (in the judgment of all Divines) if it be <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>if it be</hi> not <hi>cauſeleſs;</hi> now poſſibly this may be the caſe of many. I remember in the caſe of Marriage, <hi>Divines</hi> diſtinguiſh between <hi>Repudiation</hi> and <hi>Divorce; Divorce,</hi> they ſay, can only be for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery;</hi> but <hi>Repudiation</hi> may be lawful and neceſſary in ſeveral other caſes; in ſhort, in all caſes where it appears; there <hi>ought to have been no Union,</hi> had it been known; as ſuppoſe,
<list>
                  <item>1. One had Married another (through deceit) of his or her own Sex.</item>
                  <item>2. His very near Relation, as <hi>Mother, Siſter,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. or 3dly.</item>
               </list>
One appearing evidently unfit for the chief ends of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I think the ſame is to be ſaid in this caſe. Let us try a little: Suppoſe Chriſtians by an error, had choſen a man to be their Paſtor, and ordinarily heard him, and communicated in the Lords Supper with him, whom at laſt they found to be <hi>no Miniſter.</hi> And when they diſcover it ſhould leave him: This I hope were no <hi>ſinful ſeparation.</hi> If any ſhall ſay it is, he ſhould complain
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33146:39"/>and have him orderly removed. We will ſuppoſe the caſe ſo, that it could not be obtained: Of this the late times gave us ſome inſtances. 2. <hi>Secondly:</hi> Suppoſe Chriſtians, by an errour, and <hi>through ignorance,</hi> had done the like to one, whom after they diſcover to be corrupt in matter of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſuppoſe ſome points of <hi>Popery, Arminianiſme, Socinianiſme,</hi> which they in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences judge falſe, and makes a trade of this. Is it a ſin for them to go to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Miniſter, not being able to get this removed? 'Tis plain, they ought not to have choſen him as their Paſtor. 3. Suppoſe Chriſtians by an error, have ſo choſen and joyned with one whom they then judged of a very ſober life, but they find him a notorious <hi>Drunkard, Swearer,</hi> &amp;c. Such a one ought not to have been choſen, but doth <hi>factum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> here; muſt they not leave him? If any ſay they may have him removed, I deſire to know by <hi>what Law of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? if he be neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick.</hi> I am miſtaken if I have not read or heard the Law allows no other
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33146:39"/>caſes (or very few) of <hi>Deprivation.</hi> 4. Suppoſe Chriſtians by the like Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to have choſen one, who they thought would have been faithful <hi>watching his Flock,</hi> and to that end <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting with them,</hi> the thing of the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> (ſaith our Author) <hi>and that is Divine for Members of the ſame Church;</hi> but they find, he rarely comes near them, or rarely Preacheth to them if amongſt them, poſſibly once a moneth, hardly more, ſeldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver adminiſtring other Ordinances. In this caſe may Chriſtians depart to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea, or no? will any ſay <hi>No</hi> ſtill? then he is bound to live without God's Ordinances all his life time for ought I know.</p>
            <p>§. 60. But laſtly: Muſt it appear <hi>demonſtratively,</hi> or <hi>is it enough for it to appear to the Chriſtian probably,</hi> (that is ſo far as his Conſcience can diſcern or judge) <hi>ſinful to Communicate with a Church, before he ſeparates from it.</hi> If any ſay <hi>Demonſtratively,</hi> let him prove it: will any ſay it is enough, as to his practice? if it <hi>propably appears ſo;</hi> then
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33146:40"/>why are we ſo boldly called <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> before our <hi>probable Arguments</hi> be made appear to us, to have no probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to? But <hi>They are the people,</hi> and <hi>have ſaid Wiſdom ſhall dye with them.</hi> We muſt be <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>ſinful Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts,</hi> and for no other reaſon, but becauſe <hi>they ſay ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 61. Once more. If it be <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> for the Members of a Chuch to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Miniſter and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to which they are united: Then it is <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> for <hi>Miniſters alſo to ſeparate from the Congregations to which they were once ſo united,</hi> unleſs at leaſt commanded by the Governours of the Church, for the publick good: If any ſay No, he will, I hope, give us a Reaſon; is not the Miniſter U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited? Doth not he break the Union, yea deſtroy the <hi>Organical Church by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving,</hi> which private Chriſtians do not? I am afraid the Author will rather quit us from <hi>Schiſme,</hi> from <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Societies,</hi> than grant us the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to the prejudice of, if not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet of ſo many of his Friends,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33146:40"/>One of them he muſt do, if I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſenſe. Will our Author think to excuſe this, by ſaying, <hi>It is no Schiſme in them, becauſe they but remove to Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the ſame Communion</hi> (which he ſaid before, for peoples removing from one Pariſh to another)? It lyes upon him to prove that perſons agreeing in the ſame Doctrine, and in the ſame acts of Worſhip, though they differ in the <hi>words</hi> and <hi>ſyllables,</hi> and <hi>forms</hi> (of mere humane conſtitution) be of a different communion from their Brethren, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and are but Siſter-Churches of the ſame Communion with their Brethren, not ſeparated from them.</p>
            <p>§. 62. The Author of the <hi>Reflections</hi> had told the Author, That themſelves <hi>with us had ſeparated from</hi> Rome, <hi>which yet they, or ſome of them acknowledg</hi> a <hi>True Church:</hi> Therefore we might ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate <hi>from a True Church.</hi> The ſum of his Anſwer is
<list>
                  <item>1. That the <hi>Presbyterians do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg it ſo, to whom he ſpake.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33146:41"/>
                  <item>2. <hi>This was a current Argument of the Presbyterians againſt the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>He meant ſuch true Churches as our Parochial Congregations.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>They prove the Communion of</hi> Rome <hi>is corrupt; we only ſay theirs is.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Many <hi>do hold the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>truely a Church,</hi> not a true Church; <hi>true as to the Eſſence,</hi> but <hi>not Morally true</hi> as to <hi>her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Worſhip.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>We did not ſeparate from</hi> Rome, <hi>for we really were never of them; we reformed our ſelves without ſeparating from</hi> Rome.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe Anſwers (except the laſt) which I ſhall ſhew weak enough. Thus much we have gained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is Lawful in ſome caſes to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from a body that is Metaphyſically a true Church, that is truly a Church,</hi> which is all was intended to be gained. That the general Notion of the <hi>Truth
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33146:41"/>of a Church,</hi> ſhould be no more a <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> to prove us <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> now let us examine his particular Anſwers.</p>
            <p>§. 62. <q>
                  <hi>The</hi> Presbyterians <hi>do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg</hi> Rome <hi>a true Church,</hi>
               </q> and therefore he argued <hi>ad homines.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I find Mr. <hi>Caudry,</hi> to his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary granting ſomething of the <hi>Truth of a Church</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> crying <hi>Viderit ipſe,</hi> but he is not the mouth of all <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> did ever any know a <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> Ordaining a Miniſter the ſecond time, becauſe he was the firſt time Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> yet he was there ordained to <hi>offer Sacrifice,</hi> but alſo <hi>to Preach the Goſpel,</hi> which makes them afraid of it; or <hi>Baptizing</hi> any that turn'd <hi>Proteſtants</hi> from <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Till he had known this, he ſhould have forborne this Anſwer, it may be that many of them will grant ſhe hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the <hi>Metaphyſical Verity</hi> of a Church. A rotten Houſe, and falling, but yet an Houſe ſtill, and we think Chriſtians from ſuch a Church may with-draw.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33146:42"/>
            <p>§. 63. <hi>But this was an Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the</hi> Independents. Produce a place where they ever ſaid, It was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for Chriſtians to depart from a Church that had the leaſt of truth in it. But he ſays he meant <hi>ſuch as our Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Congregations,</hi> this is a general: what doth he mean by <hi>ſuch?</hi> 4. <hi>They prove the Communion of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>corrupt; we only ſay it of theirs.</hi> And he only ſays that we only ſay it. We think that many have proved that we cannot <hi>Communicate</hi> or <hi>Miniſter</hi> in it under ſome preſent circumſtances, without what we judge ſin. Who ſhall determine betwixt us as to our practice? Hath this Author made, or can he ſhew us a ſtrict Anſwer to <hi>Calderwood, Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſpy,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Ames?</hi> and yet much more is to be ſaid in our caſe, then they could ſpeak.</p>
            <p>§. 64. Many do ſay that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Vere,</hi> but not <hi>Vera Eccleſia,</hi> (that will not do) we can ſhew him <hi>vera,</hi> that is true as well as, <hi>Vere</hi> Truly; but his meaning is, True in <hi>Eſſence,</hi> not <hi>Morally True;</hi> what is the meaning of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33146:42"/>that? Not <hi>true in her Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip.</hi> This kind of truth admitts many degrees. <hi>We would fain know of our Author to what degree of moral truth that Church muſt be arrived, from which he judgeth it ſinful to ſeparate;</hi> for we ſhall find that divers of his Brethren and Fathers have acknowledged a great degree of moral truth <hi>in the Church of</hi> Rome, from which yet they ſeparated, and we believe died in their <hi>ſeparation</hi> from it. Died <hi>they as Fools dyed?</hi> Let me ſhew this a little: Was not the Church of <hi>Rome morally true,</hi> becauſe an <hi>Antichriſtian-Church,</hi> and the Seat of the <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> So indeed Biſhop <hi>Downame,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> and many Biſhops were wont to ſay; but ſince that time Biſhop <hi>Mountagne</hi> hath called their Arguments <hi>Apocaliptycal</hi> phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies. <hi>Dow</hi> ſaith it is doubtful. Dr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> ſaith it <hi>cannot be,</hi> for <hi>Antichriſt</hi> muſt be a <hi>ſingle man,</hi> a <hi>Jew</hi> that muſt kill <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Star Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Speech; <hi>p. 32.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> confeſſeth therefore he hath raced <hi>out of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, the</hi> ſcandalous term <hi>Antichriſtian Sect.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:33146:43"/>
            <p>§. 65. Is the fault in the <hi>Doctrine of the Church of</hi> Rome; it may be ſome of us think there is fault enough there; I truſt our Author himſelf thinks ſo, but neither all former Conformiſts, nor preſent Conformiſts believe that <hi>ſhe differs from us in any Fundamentals.</hi> I my ſelf have been told ſo within few years; the Author could not but know that Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Potter,</hi> and many others have thus far aſſerted her <hi>Moral truth</hi> again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as to <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Now may not that be put for a Problem amongſt thoſe who are ſo Zealous in this point.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Whither it be not Schiſmatical to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from a Church upon the account of Doctrine which errs in no funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet thoſe great men confeſſed the latter, and did the former. If we looſe this ſtand, I know not where we ſhall find a <hi>boundary</hi> to ſtop us from <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> from <hi>a true Church,</hi> for any one falſe Propoſition of Doctrine maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it. But what <hi>Doctrine</hi> is there, as to which we cannot ſhew them that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33146:43"/>ſome or other our conforming <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Brethren</hi> have not either acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged true in <hi>their terms,</hi> or <hi>ſo far true,</hi> as would make ſeparation for it dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; yet all theſe ſeparated from it, and died many of them in that <hi>black Schiſme</hi> (if it were ſo.) Let the <hi>Author</hi> inſtance, and he ſhall hear what we can ſay to it; he will I hope, ſpare the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian points.</hi> The Doctrine of <hi>Faith</hi> as an <hi>aſſent</hi> only to the Propoſition, <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Works,</hi> &amp;c. but let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p>§. 66. But it may be the buſineſs is, they have acknowledged and proved her Communion unlawful as to <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> we indeed do ſo think it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſinful. But have all thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts ſeparated from her thought ſo? we think ſo, becauſe we judge her ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous in her Adoration of the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, The Saints departed, Reliques, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, Altars,</hi> &amp;c. and we know that many of our conforming Brethren are of the ſame mind with us, Dr. <hi>Brewynt,</hi> Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> and many others have ſufficiently told us ſo; but the queſtion
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33146:44"/>is, whether all our <hi>conforming Brethren,</hi> who have ſeparated thus, judged her thus <hi>morally</hi> not <hi>a true</hi> Church. What meant Dr. <hi>Heylins</hi> four bowings at his taking up and ſetting down the <hi>Bread and Wine in the Euchariſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heylins <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Anſwer,</hi> p. 137.</note> What ſaith the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Weights and Meaſures,</hi> as to the point of <hi>Veneration of Images?</hi> What ſaith Biſhop <hi>Mountague,</hi> Antig. <hi>p.</hi> 318. and in his <hi>Antid.</hi> p. 30. and in his <hi>Orig.</hi> p. 40. he ſays the Ancient Church did <hi>Venerate Reliques,</hi> Antid. <hi>p.</hi> 44. but I will enlarge no further till I have particular inſtances given.</p>
            <p>§. 67. We ſee it was the judgment of theſe men, (and they were learned men) <hi>that we may ſeparate from a Church that hath a great degree of moral truth.</hi> But it may be they thought they did not ſeparate becauſe they and their Fore-fathers were <hi>really never of them,</hi> but <hi>reformed themſelves.</hi> But were not our Fore-fathers <hi>Baptized into that Church?</hi> Did not the Laws of <hi>England</hi> once tye us to them? Were we not U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33146:44"/>to the <hi>Governours Worſhip, Members,</hi> and <hi>Aſſemblies of that Church.</hi> Did not our Fore-fathers <hi>ſhew</hi> their <hi>conſent</hi> by ordinary attendance upon their <hi>Devotions,</hi> &amp;c. This is all our Author ſaith for our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> to the <hi>National and Parochial Church, or Churches</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§. 68. Again, they have proved it, he ſaith, that <hi>Communion in that Church is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt.</hi> How? Becauſe we cannot commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with it without ſin. How have they proved it? Demonſtratively; ſo as the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries cannot deny it? Nothing leſs, they do deny it, and yet diſpute it, but ſo as <hi>we probably judg it ſinful.</hi> We grant this is proved, and ſo we think we have proved it too, though it may be more ſinful to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the Romiſh Church. But we know <hi>Magis &amp; minus non variant ſpeciem.</hi> But we think we ought not to do the leaſt ſin.</p>
            <p>§. 69. But we do not ſay it is <hi>ſinful</hi> to <hi>communicate with them in all Ordinances. Why do we not communicate with them ſo far as we can without ſin?</hi> Presbyterians indeed do generally acknowledg ſo much. But Communion is either <hi>ſtated</hi> and fixed, or <hi>Occaſional.</hi> They conceive themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, <hi>ſtatedly</hi> and <hi>fixedly,</hi> if they can, to <hi>communicate</hi> to their proper Congregations where they can enjoy all the Ordinances of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33146:45"/>God. For <hi>occaſional Communion,</hi> they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have denied it, nor ſhall deny it to their Brethren in ſuch actions wherein their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences will allow them ſo to communicate without ſin, as occaſion offers it ſelf; they acknowledg many of their Miniſters, and of their Churches, <hi>true Churches,</hi> true <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Churches;</hi> they many of them hear them <hi>Preach</hi> and <hi>Pray,</hi> and bring their Children to them to be <hi>Baptized</hi> (<hi>eſpecially</hi> if any of them will abate what in that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration none judgeth by <hi>Divine</hi> precept Originally neceſſary, and they judg ſinful?) what would the Author have more, unleſs a perfect communion?</p>
            <p>§. 70. As to which (though I do not much value Arguments from Authority of men, becauſe they never touch the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor <hi>ad homines;</hi> becauſe they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>Bullets,</hi> and hit but one perſon; yet once let me uſe one. Becauſe our Author in his Doctrine of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> p. 28. aſſures us he is much of Mr. <hi>Fulwoods</hi> mind. I know not that <hi>Reverend Perſon;</hi> but I take him to be the ſame Mr. <hi>Fulwood</hi> that was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Miniſter at <hi>Staple Fitzpane</hi> in <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-ſhire,</hi> and <hi>anno,</hi> 1652. publiſhed a Book called, <hi>The Churches and Miniſtry of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>true Churches, and a true Miniſtry</hi> (if he be not the man intended, I beg his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33146:45"/>if it be he, he ſaith thus of the <hi>Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>For matters of Government, indeed of late we were under Epiſcopacy, all whoſe appurtenances ſavoured of Antichriſt</hi>—and in the ſame page a little after—our <hi>Epiſcopal Courts, Service, Tyranny,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were very groſs.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This was Mr. <hi>Fulwoods</hi> judgment. I think we may eaſily argue according to his principles. It is Mr. <hi>Fulwoods</hi> aſſertion, not ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From a Church, all whoſe appurtenances, as to Government, ſavour of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fulwoods</hi> Churches &amp; Miniſtry of <hi>England</hi> true, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 12.</note> and whoſe <hi>ſervice is very groſs. Chriſtians may, and ought to ſeparate,</hi> ſo far as to <hi>that Government, all whoſe appurtenances ſo ſavour,</hi> and whoſe <hi>ſervice is groſs.</hi> But ſaith Mr. <hi>Fulwood,</hi> &amp;.—<hi>Ergo.</hi> When the <hi>Reverend</hi> Author hath found out an anſwer for his Friend Mr. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> we will further examin it. But there is no end of theſe things.</p>
            <p>§ 71. In the mean time I muſt mind the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of too little candor, as to his Adverſary who wrote the <hi>Reflexions,</hi> in ſaying the ſum of what he offered, was reducible <hi>to theſe two propoſitions.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the Conformiſts held the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to be a true Church,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33146:46"/>yet did ſeparate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That <hi>our Parochial Churches are no true Churches,</hi> when as he never ſaid the <hi>latter at all,</hi> but the clean contrary, and had acknowledged,
<list>
                        <item>1. All of them <hi>true Churches,</hi> that is, <hi>true parts</hi> of the Catholick Church.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Many</hi> of them <hi>true Miniſterial Churches.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>Some of them true Organical Churches.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
Beſides this, He that reads the Authors <hi>chap.</hi> 1. will ſee theſe two things were not the <hi>ſum</hi> of what he ſaid, and that how little ſoever <hi>Reaſon</hi> was in thoſe <hi>Reflections,</hi> there was yet more then this Author in his <hi>Remarques</hi> was pleaſed to take notice of, for that Author had then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on their not being united to Parochial Churches.</p>
            <p>§. 72. To ſhut up this diſcourſe, I from my Soul wiſh, all the Lords, Miniſters, and People of <hi>England</hi> were of <hi>one heart and mind.</hi> I am not of <hi>Gravity</hi> or <hi>Learning</hi> ſufficient to Adviſe either Conformiſts or Non-conformiſts, but ſhall only propoſe my own thoughts, and not mine alone. The Reverend and Learned Dr. <hi>Hornbeck,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in his Diſſertations <hi>de Epiſcopatu,</hi> hath theſe paſſages which <hi>I</hi> ſhall tranſlate. The learned may read them in the Printed Copies.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>If men were every where as ſollicitous for forming and reforming men, and fitting them for the ſacred Miniſtry, to which they
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33146:46"/>profeſs to give up themſelves, the diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about the form of Sacred Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment would be more eaſie, and leſs evil need be feared from that which we judge not ſo good.—Here,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>We muſt begin that men may be made worthy for the work,</hi> and Parag. 4.—<hi>Here we muſt lay on our help—We ſee the Apoſtles in their Writings, were more ſollicitous about the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues than the degrees of Miniſters,</hi>—Parag. 9. <hi>Before</hi> (ſaith he) we divide into parties <hi>about other things,</hi> we ſhould <hi>joyntly agree about theſe things. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of common Doctrine according to truth and piety, ſhould be either ſet forth or confirmed, then exact Canons ſhould be made about the whole life and manners of Miniſters, and then a diſputation about the form of Church Government ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi>—Thus far he.</q>
            </p>
            <p>§. 73. I ſhall conclude with delivering my Opinion, That if 1. <hi>All the ancient Canons</hi> of <hi>Councils</hi> were <hi>executed,</hi> which concern <hi>Miniſters Lives</hi> and <hi>Office.</hi> And the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> as expounded by King <hi>James</hi> and the <hi>Parliament of</hi> England were avowed, and thoſe men might have nothing to do in the debate. Who are <hi>dead in Law,</hi> according to thoſe <hi>Canons;</hi> that is, ſuch as ought to be <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived,</hi> and who had declared, or ſhould
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33146:47"/>declare themſelves contrary to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſo <hi>expound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and declared.</hi> The remaining part would quickly ſo well agree with other things, as we ſhould be no more troubled with clamours of <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Separation;</hi> and tell ſomthing of that Nature be, I ſee no <hi>medium,</hi> but either <hi>Diſſenters</hi> muſt be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged,</hi> and <hi>Schiſme clamour'd</hi> and <hi>never proved,</hi> or ſuffering for <hi>Conſcience-ſake</hi> muſt be impoſed and patiently endured.</p>
            <q>Fiat Voluntas Dei.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:33146:47"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. l. 23. f. <hi>curare,</hi> r. <hi>curaes,</hi> p. 32. l. 14. f. <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> r. <hi>Arminius,</hi> p. 33. l. 4. f. 130. r. 13th. p. 36. l. 12. f. <hi>generatibus,</hi> r. <hi>Generalibus,</hi> p. 42. l. 12. f. <hi>Jundical,</hi> r. <hi>Juridical,</hi> p. 70. l. 2. r. <hi>one Miniſters parts,</hi> p. 74. l. 9. r. <hi>he Preach ſome,</hi> p. 75. l. <hi>ult,</hi> r. <hi>probably.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ERRATA,</hi> in the Two laſt Sheets.</p>
            <p>PAge. 10. l. 14. after the word <hi>Apology,</hi> I pray add this, <hi>That which is of Divine, is undeniably greater than that which is of Humane Inſtitution,</hi> p. 4. l. 10. f. <hi>act,</hi> r. <hi>acts,</hi> p. 27. l. 19. f. <hi>page</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 34. r. <hi>B.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 34. p. 29. l. 22. f. <hi>Affirmations,</hi> r. <hi>Affirmatives.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:33146:48"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33146:48"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> Account of the Non-Conformiſts Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for Divine Worſhip, by, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> according to his <hi>Middle-Way,</hi> againſt Dean <hi>F's</hi> charge of Schiſme; and of the freedome of Conſcience, from unuſefull Laws, and the power of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint againſt his Exceptions.</head>
            <p>HAving written four Papers which being bound together I call <hi>Mediocria,</hi> and finding in the end of one of them an Advertiſement about a Book Entituled <hi>Two Points of great Moment,</hi> (which was the <hi>Obligation of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws,</hi> and the <hi>Authority of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in the matters of Religion,</hi>) by me <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed:</hi> I think it but civill to take an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity (while it is in my mind) of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning my acknowledgments to the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and worthy <hi>Dr. &amp; Dean,</hi> the Author of <hi>Tolleration not to be abuſed</hi> for his reſpectful Animadverſions, in referrence (I count) to both theſe Points, in his <hi>Advice to Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33146:49"/>and Non-Conformiſts.</hi> I confeſs my ſelf obliged to him for it, and to requite the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, I will preſent him with two things: my anſwer to what he hath put in againſt me, and an Apology, according to my Middle Temper, for the Non-Conformiſt in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter above named.</p>
            <p>I will begin with the Laſt firſt, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is of moſt preſent import and it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fit I ſhould preferr that of the <hi>Publick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my <hi>Private</hi> Vindication. There are diverſe ſorts of the Non-Conformiſts, and they have their Meetings we know, not all on the ſame Reaſons. There are ſome who have been and are for our Parochial Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who are ſatisfied with their Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and, if they might have freedome, would ſtill chooſe them: And there are others that are in their inclinations for the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall way only. For my part I profeſs my Self of the former Sort, and do here declare in the behalf of my Self and many others of my Brethren, that we do not go from our <hi>Pariſh</hi> Church or Miniſter, in oppoſition to them, as if ſuch Congregations were not Churches; No, we are ſenſible when our Lord hath commanded that the Tares ſhould not be pluckt up for fear of endangering even but <hi>Some</hi> of the Wheat, what a grievous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure it may like to be to him, if we ſhould go to Root up <hi>all the Wheat</hi> for fear of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33146:49"/>Tares, which to Unchurch whole Pariſhes were to do: Nor is it out of Pride, Vanity, Oſtentation, Faction, or Self-advantage that we do it: We could not anſwer a leſſer Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s, then a <hi>Dean's</hi> charge againſt us, if we did ſo. Two things therefore I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, That our Pariſh-Churches are true Churches: And that it is our Duty conſequently to deſire and endeavour their Union and Proſperity. And what would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Conformiſt have of me more, unleſs it be alſo to joyn with them there in the Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Ordinances, which I refuſe not neither upon convenient occaſion? Well! Upon what ground then ſhall I offer my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for the Cauſe I have here under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken? Why I will give it very impartially. As I grant theſe two things to be our duty, ſo muſt I aſſume that which will not, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied me, that it is the duty likewiſe of thoſe who are ſet apart to the office of the Miniſtry (ſuppoſing them in every reſpect fit for the Work, to have a call to it, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Sincerity does not at preſent other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe direct) to preach the Goſpel, by way of diſcharge of that office. We have the Apoſtles expreſs authority and example for this, who when they where Threatned and Commanded by the Magiſtrates to <hi>Speak no more in Chriſt's name,</hi> they have left us their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33146:50"/>anſwer on record, <hi>Whether it be meet to obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or You, judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> Now I muſt lay down this rule, that when two duties come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo that we cannot perform the one, but we muſt omit the other, the greater duty muſt take Place of the leſs. The rule appears in it's own light, and alſo from Scripture. <hi>I will have Mercy</hi> (ſayes God) <hi>and not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi> What is the meaning but that when act of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> fall in, ſuch duties as that of <hi>Sacrifice</hi> which are leſs muſt give way. Here then is our caſe plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which of theſe is the greater duty? We are to ſeek Unity, and to Preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. If we keep our Pariſh Churches, we muſt not Preach the Goſpel: If we Preach the Goſpel, we muſt go to theſe Private Meetings. Which of theſe is indeed of greateſt concernment to the glory of God, and the Peoples Salvation? <hi>In General</hi> which is the greateſt Matter that the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus be Preached: Or the Union of our Pariſh-Churches be promoted? In <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,</hi> whether ſhall I, or any other Non-Conformiſt who have a call upon occaſion to Preach at ſuch a time, place, or Company, do more Service unto God by going &amp; doing it: or by refuſing and going to my Pariſh-Church, for the ſake of Unity, for which I have ſtill other Seaſons? And which is the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33146:50"/>
               <hi>greater Evil</hi> to have a people of a Pariſh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into ſeveral places to hear the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of both Perſwaſions Preach to them (when this too ſhall not hinder them being parts ſtill, or Members of the ſame Church): Or that all the Preachers or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the Nation but thoſe only who <hi>Conform</hi> ſhould have their Mouths ſtopped or their Talents buried? How! when there is ſo many of them! So many of them truly ſerious and painful Labourers! So many of them that actually do ſo much good, and the ever-laſting welfare of thouſands of men's Souls depend upon it? What is <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in compariſon! I will appeal to the Conſcience of every upright equal man, whether Conformiſt or Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, that fears God, to give Judgment. For the charge then of this Dean which he ſeems to have managed ſo ſtrenuouſly, I anſwer. Schiſme is a <hi>Cauſleſs Breach of the Churches <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, or a cauſleſs ſeparation from her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> the Communion of a Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are Members, or ſhould be. Let this learned man, or any other that hath read any thing about Schiſme tell me, if <hi>I</hi> do not define it right by a Separation that is <hi>Cauſleſs,</hi> for if there be a cauſe, the Separation will be juſtified, as it is between us and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33146:51"/>Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now when the caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Conformiſt and us is ſo open and in the face of the Sun, that unleſs we Countenance or allow of thoſe Meetings which are Locally Diſtinct from our Pariſh-Congregations, the whole generation of the Non-Conformiſt Miniſters muſt be laid by, from the exerciſe of their office for ought <hi>I</hi> ſee as long as theſe men do hold, whatſoever becomes in the mean time of the Souls of ſo many multitudes: what apology, defence, or <hi>Account</hi> do we need more but this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? <hi>Is there not a cauſe?</hi> They are the words of <hi>David</hi> to his ſurly Elder Brethren, that are offended only for his being about the buſineſs he was ſent. <hi>And David ſaid, what have I done? Is there not a Cauſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible that there is much more may be ſaid, or that there are other Pleas which may be made by the Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt for their Meetings then this I offer. I have (<hi>I</hi> know) propoſed my ſelf a little in another Paper, towards ſome Catholick Healing of us, even under our <hi>ſtated Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> if they cannot be helpt. If they can, or if this be enough, it is this Plea <hi>I</hi> chooſe, as the moſt indifferent between the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt and us, the moſt fair and conducive to our Uniting again, if God give that Grace to the Nation. And this (under pardon) <hi>I</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33146:51"/>will be ſo bold, as to name <hi>my</hi> Plea, Mr. <hi>H's,</hi> Plea, Of <hi>Greater Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is a number of ſuch as own, or believe in the Lord Jeſus, and joyn in Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the glorifying his Name in ſubmiſſion to his Ordinances. Theſe Societies are either <hi>Particular,</hi> or that which conſiſts of them all, the Church <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi> Of the Church as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> Chriſt is the Head, from whom we have theſe Ordinances: &amp;, when the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are Parochial, &amp; others that meet ſeparately from them, do both conſent or unite in his Ordinances, that is, in the ſame <hi>Doctrine</hi> (ſo far as is neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) and in the ſame <hi>Worſhip,</hi> required in the <hi>Word,</hi> who can deny them to be both <hi>Parts</hi> of the Univerſal Church Viſible, and ſo <hi>true Churches?</hi> As for going to diverſe places, if there be no breach of the great Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is Charity, in other reſpects, it is a matter of indifferency, &amp; can be no ground to charge Schiſme upon one more then the other. There muſt be ſome other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration than of the Church found out if they will accuſe us of Schiſme: And that is not as it is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> or <hi>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> but as it is <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Parochial.</hi> As it is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> and <hi>Particular</hi> it is <hi>ex praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> of <hi>Divine:</hi> as it is <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> it is <hi>ex providentia,</hi> of <hi>Humane</hi> and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential inſtitution. There are ſome things
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33146:52"/>required to the Church <hi>ad eſſe,</hi> and ſome things <hi>ad bene eſſe.</hi> That which is required <hi>ad eſſe,</hi> is named (a due adminiſtration of the Word, Sacrament and Prayer), and we divide not in it. That which is required <hi>ad bene eſſe</hi> is either <hi>neceſſary</hi> to that <hi>bene</hi> (or <hi>melius</hi>) <hi>eſſe,</hi> being of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> and that is ſome <hi>Diſcipline</hi> in general, though for the <hi>Sort,</hi> I will not ſay which is ſuch, or that which is <hi>accidental</hi> and <hi>accumulative</hi> from man, as to have the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrat Chriſtian,</hi> and a <hi>Nurſing Father</hi> to it, with his People generally of that Religion. The one of theſe (I ſay) is of God's <hi>Praeceptive</hi> (we ſpeak it not <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> but in regard to the Conſtitution of the Church of Chriſt): the other of his <hi>Providential will</hi> only. In this <hi>accidental</hi> regard as the Church is <hi>National</hi> do we acknowledg that the King is head of it, and hath his Ordinances in reſpect <hi>thereunto</hi> to be obeyed, as Chriſt hath in regard to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi> That the Magiſtrate hath Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Protect the Church of Chriſt, by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt's Ordinances be obſerved in every Congregation according to their way, and in looking to the whole that they do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what ſhall make to the Peace of the Nation, is out of queſtion. The King here governs by his <hi>Laws,</hi> and the Laws of this <hi>Land</hi> have appointed the conſtitution
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33146:52"/>of particular Churches to be of Pariſhes as moſt convenient to that purpoſe. If we conſent not to theſe Laws we break the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> which is of <hi>Humane</hi> inſtitution, though we preſerve that which is <hi>Divine.</hi> Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the wholeſome commands of our Superiours is ſin, and when that ſeparation therefore, which is a thing indifferent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe does become ſinful through that diſodedience, unleſs we have ſomthing to juſtify the diſobedience, ſuch ſeparation, by <hi>Analogy,</hi> is Schiſme. And here do I verily think muſt the bottom of all that can be charged upon us about Schiſme be placed. If the Parliament ſhould Legitimate theſe ſeparate Meetings by an Act, they would immediately become parts of the <hi>National Church</hi> no leſs then our Pariſhes, and that would put an end to the Schiſme; the Evil chargeable upon us any otherwiſe, being like to be found the <hi>Fault of the Perſons,</hi> not of our meetings, or of the <hi>Thing:</hi> But ſo long as they are againſt Law, it is the <hi>Obligation of humane Laws</hi> I perceive, and the <hi>Authority of the Magiſtrate about Religion</hi> are the points muſt come into <hi>Plea.</hi> Theſe have been treated and put together in a Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Two points of great Moment Diſcuſſed.</hi> The ſubſtance whereof as to my preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe will reſolve into this Diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Laws which are <hi>Wholeſome</hi> Laws, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33146:53"/>is, for the <hi>Common Good</hi> in <hi>Civil's,</hi> and for <hi>Edification</hi> in <hi>Spiritualls,</hi> do bind us under <hi>Pain of Sin.</hi> Such is the law I count for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Union, but there are two Caſes wherein we are exempted from ſuch Laws, and which juſtify the Non-Obedience. One is, when that which is commanded is againſt a man's Conſcience. The other is, when that which is commanded cannot be done, but ſome other Duty which is of greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern muſt be thruſt out, and in this Caſe (I ſay) the omitting that which is the leſſer Duty, is no ſin. In this Point, ye ſee before, I have placed our Apology. I muſt add, that foraſmuch as it is no Sin to omit a <hi>leſſer</hi> Duty for doing a <hi>greater,</hi> when both cannot be done, but to omit the greater Duty conſequently muſt be ſin: it follows, that ſuppoſing it to be Schiſme to refuſe Communion, when we may come to Church without ſin, it muſt be no Schiſme to wave it, or not to come, when if we come we ſhould ſin, as we muſt, when we ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a greater Duty by coming. <hi>Schiſme is a Voluntary Departure without cauſe given from that Chriſtian Church, whereof he was a Member; or a Breach of that Communion wherein a man might have continued without Sin,</hi> ſayes that late Author of a <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry,</hi> into the cauſes of men's contempt of the Church and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33146:53"/>A Book two fine I count to bear a Diſpute, or uphold ſo large a deſign he undertakes. <hi>I would fain know</hi> (ſayes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>by what Authority this ſeparating practiſe can be juſtified from the guilt of the moſt Horrible Schiſme that ever was heard of in the Chriſtian World.</hi> A ſober Anſwer to the new Separatiſts. <hi>Pa.</hi> 156. again (<hi>Pa.</hi> 157.) Diſtinguiſhing of a Voluntary deſertion of ones Miniſtry, and chooſing ſilence in caſe of Non-Conformity. <hi>The ſecond</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is the Illuſtration of four Cardinal Vertues, Humility, Meekneſs, Selfe-denial, Obedience.</hi> I cannot but quote theſe Paſſages as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to my Humor, nor can <hi>I</hi> forbear Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the Reading of them. Not becauſe that worthy honeſt Citizen hath not read <hi>Ethicks,</hi> in calling theſe <hi>Cardinal</hi> Vritues, whereof we know indeed there are <hi>Four,</hi> but neither of theſe is <hi>One</hi> of them: But for the Spirit, or preſent Aſſurance where-with he Writes, I could never be ſo Confident when I wrote againſt Separation. Nor can I look on this Separation only from the Churches of the <hi>Nation,</hi> not from <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Church or Churches, that is a Schiſme of mans Denomination (our Pariſhes being of Humane Contrivance out of Queſtion,) to be ſuch a <hi>Horrible Creature</hi> as he makes it. The great Bear hath been led ſo long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33146:54"/>the ſtreets that the very Children are no longer afraid of it. Neither can I think it any ſuch Vertue for a man to give over Preaching. <hi>I</hi> am mightily Flattered methinks in this Paſſage, who, if this good man be in the right, ſhould be one of the moſt Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Non-Conformiſts among all our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. <hi>I</hi> pray God to for-give me that Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue with my Manifold Aberations. <hi>I</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my Self with the Old Non-Conformiſt a <hi>Conformiſt Pariſhioner,</hi> though a <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Miniſter,</hi> and refuſe not to joyn in the Ordinances of Doctrine, Breaking Bread; and Prayers, in our Parochial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</p>
            <p>Laws which are <hi>not Wholeſome</hi> Laws, that is, not for the <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Temporal</hi> good of the Community (ſuch as our Ceremonies &amp; the like things I count be) may, I Preſume, entangle the Mind and Oblige the <hi>outward Man</hi> to ſuffering, or to doing rather then Suffer, if they be not <hi>Sinful</hi> to us, as well as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable,</hi> but they do not (I have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and muſt deſend ſtill what I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined as of neceſſary import to tender Chriſtians) oblige the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the Subject. And ſo I deſcend to my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Concernment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. H. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith, that unleſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> matter of the Princes Command be antecedently neceſſary in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33146:54"/>Judgment of the Subject, it obliges not the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> Sir! This is a miſtake, I ſay not ſo. I ſay indeed, that unleſs a Law be for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good, it binds not in point of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and I give theſe two reaſons for it. The one, becauſe the Magiſtrate hath no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from God but for our <hi>Weale,</hi> nor the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop but for our <hi>Edification.</hi> The other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are to ſuppoſe the Superiours will, or intention, is meaſured by his Authority: And when the thing commanded is not for our Good or Edification, as it is deſtitute of God's Authority, it muſt be ſuppoſed void alſo of <hi>his Miniſters</hi> intention. See my <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of humane Laws, Pa.</hi> 139. with <hi>pa.</hi> 25. But that I ſhould be made upon this to hold therefore (and that for a Principle) that the Conſcience is only Obliged from the <hi>Matter of the thing Commanded,</hi> and not from the <hi>Command of the Magiſtrate,</hi> is ſuch an abuſe and weakneſs, as the modeſty of thoſe Words <hi>[You ſeem to Say]</hi> will not excuſe. There are a Thouſand things good for the Publick, which, being not command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are not neceſſary, nor Oblige any Body. The controverſie between Conformiſt and Non-Conformiſt is ſuppoſed to be about things indifferent, in which the Conſcience is Free, and not Bound, till our Superiours Command comes. It is by the Authority
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33146:55"/>then of our Superiour (I ſay) derived from God, that the Conſcience is obliged: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that before the Command there is no Obligation: and when he commands, the matter of the command muſt be ſuch as he hath Power to Command in, or it is void. It is <hi>Authoritas imperantis agnita</hi> (<hi>I</hi> have noted it ſome-where) is the <hi>Objectum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male obedientiae,</hi> and anſwereth the queſtion, <hi>Qûare obedis?</hi> But <hi>I am not aware</hi> (ſaith the kind <hi>Dean</hi>) <hi>That obedience to man in things indifferent is commanded of God in Scripture.</hi> Yes! I am aware that Things indifferent (by which we mean whatſoever is neither commanded nor for-bidden in the <hi>Word,</hi>) are either for the <hi>Common good,</hi> and ſo the ſubject matter of the Superiours Authority, and Obedience to men in ſuch things is commanded by God in Scripture: Or they are <hi>not</hi> for the common Good, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and in ſuch matters, neither hath the Superiour Authority (<hi>I</hi> ſay) from God to command them, nor can ſuch commands for that reaſon be obligatory to the Conſcience. But <hi>Obedience to them is alſo required in the Law</hi> of <hi>Nature for the common Good.</hi> How? Is Obedience required by the law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the common Good, to things which I ſuppoſe not for the common Good? Why, <hi>It is for the ſecurity of the Publick
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33146:55"/>peace, and God's own Vicegerency on Earth.</hi> I anſwer, The Honour of the Magiſtrate, and ſecurity of the Government is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (and the common good thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd) in our <hi>obedience,</hi> when the Laws are <hi>wholeſome</hi> Laws; in our <hi>ſuffering,</hi> when they are <hi>ſinful</hi> Laws; in our <hi>avoiding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcandal,</hi> when they are <hi>unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Laws; in our ſubjection to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity reſiding in the Perſon under <hi>all</hi> Laws ſo that when he will, he can enforce them. Upon this account, there is a difference or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily between the <hi>Command</hi> of a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> or <hi>Parent,</hi> and the <hi>Laws of a Nation. A Command</hi> to a Child or Servant, does ſuppoſe, <hi>a do it, or I'le make you.</hi> If the Magiſtrate ſets himſelf to have a Law obeyed by a particular perſon, the caſe is the ſame; and ſeeing the honour of the Governour and the Government it ſelf is ſtill (I count) concern'd in this, that he ſhould be able to make his Subjects obey, if he <hi>put his power out,</hi> and the thing be no Sin, Obedience being for the common good, in ſuch a caſe, a man is obliged to it in Conſcience: but if he do not, a <hi>Law</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes only the common good mainly to be entended, prudence to be uſed, no contempt offered, and the will of the Magiſtrate is done. When our Obedience then (I ſay)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33146:56"/>does indeed ſerve thoſe ends he mentions (and greater be not ſerved, or the ſame otherwiſe better ſerved) we are obliged: But what if it ſerves them not? What if my impertinent Obedience ſhall but diſturb the Peace (or the peaceable) and reflect diſhonour on the Law-giver? what if it ſhould do more hurt than good, taking one thing with another? when it is not for the common good, I ſay, and then only, that we are not obliged in Conſcience.</p>
            <p>There are a few more words here need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe we are at the bottom. How far the Laws of man do bind the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, was the queſtion, That the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not bound at all by humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, hath been the opinion of no few Doctors, nor mean perſons: for in the Act for the <hi>VVedneſday</hi> faſt, it ſeems to have been the received judgment at that time of the whole Nation. <hi>I ſay theſe faſts</hi> (or the like appointments) <hi>are to be obſerved, yet ſhall not the breaking them, make a man to do deadly ſin, except in his mind be ſome other malicious affection therewith an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, as raſhneſs of mind, deſpite, or ſuch like; for ſo much as no poſitive Law of man made without foundation of Scripture, may bind any perſon, ſo that in breaking ſuch he ſhall therefore ſin deadly. John Lambert</hi> the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33146:56"/>
               <hi>Martyr.</hi> So <hi>Luther,</hi> and the Proteſtants I ſuppoſe ordinarily after <hi>Gerſon.</hi> See <hi>Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> ſee <hi>Field. They do impiouſly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp and aſſume to themſelves, that which is proper to God; who will have their Lawes bind the Conſcience, and threaten Damnation to the Offendors,</hi> ſayes that learned Dr for our Currant Doctrine; who does therefore quote alſo two Papiſts. <hi>Human Lawes binds the Conſcience not, Ex voluntate Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatoris, ſed ex ipſa legum utilitate &amp; ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> Stapleton Cont. 5. De pot. Ec <hi>circa leges</hi> Mor. Quaeſt. 7. Art. 2. <hi>Quamvis peccet quis tranſgrediendo leges humanas, non tamen ligant conſcientiam: patet per ſimile de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis medicorum, quae deſpicere quis non poteſt ſine peccato, &amp; tamen non ligant conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</hi> Gerſon <hi>De vita ſpir. anim.</hi> Lect. 4. If you think this too large, that the Lawes of Man, however, ſhould not be made to oblige the Conſcience <hi>in equality</hi> with the Lawes of God, is but moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; That they do oblige therefore only ſo far, as to the <hi>avoiding contempt and ſcandal,</hi> hath been our moſt conſtant deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination (I think) againſt the Papiſts. Now I would willingly know here, upon what bottom ſuch a Determination is laid; and that which offers it ſelf, is this. That whereas all Lawes do oblige only, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33146:57"/>to the <hi>will</hi> of the Law-giver, it is ſuppoſed that he entends we ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged <hi>ſo far</hi> only. But I pray why do we ſet theſe limits to his will? why may we not ſuppoſe as well, that he entends his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation with other limits, to wit, that his Lawes ſhall bind us ſo far, as ſtands with our convenience; or ſo far as the hurt or damage to us, does not exceed the good we ſhall do the Community by our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? If our <hi>Superiour</hi> entends not to bind us ſo far, as God does by <hi>his Lawes,</hi> but ſo far as, the ſupream Law of Charity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires (See <hi>Davinants</hi> Determinations, <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 20. <hi>p.</hi> 100.) why may we not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe other limits (I ſay) as well as theſe mentioned? The truth is, there is no bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom in the buſineſs, till we come to that I have laid, which is this, that foraſmuch as God hath entruſted no Authority with any to give Lawes, but for the <hi>Peoples welfare,</hi> and this is the end therefore of all Lawes, there are no Men in capacity of Law-givers (eſpecially a Parliament that repreſent the Community) but are to be ſuppoſed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this altogether: and conſequently if a Law prove otherwiſe, or is againſt the common good, it muſt be ſuppoſed alſo, that ſuch a Law is devoid of their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or is not according to their will, and ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33146:57"/>does not bind the Conſcience, even upon this double ground; both becauſe it is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Authority it ſhould have from <hi>God,</hi> and its Authority from the <hi>will of Man</hi> alſo, upon the account declared. That the <hi>will</hi> of the Law-giver ſhould be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his <hi>Authority,</hi> is but meet (I hope) to be <hi>ſuppoſed:</hi> and this laſt ground, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having been but once touched in my Book before quoted, I do imprint it now more ſenſibly in this Paper.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs I have heard it ſaid to me, by One or Two, ſometimes thus, When a thing is indeed <hi>deſtructive to the publick good,</hi> we will grant you what you ſay; but not ſo, when a thing is only <hi>againſt it,</hi> or not <hi>for it.</hi> I reply, Sirs! I pray let us come to a bottome, This is not to go to the bottome. Why ſhall not a command <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the common good bind the Conſcience? If it be ſin to diſobey, we muſt not <hi>ſin</hi> to avoid <hi>miſchief,</hi> we muſt ſay therefore it is not ſin. And why is it not ſin, but becauſe ſuch a Command hath none of God's Authority? I muſt aſſume, ſo hath no Command that is not for the common good; for the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that any Man hath from God, is only for our Good, for our <hi>Edification.</hi> Here is the bottome, if it be firm, it muſt hold throughout; if not, it muſt not hold at all.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33146:58"/>
               <hi>He is the Miniſter of God for our good. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the power given to us of God for Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Dean's Texts, I have anſwered, <hi>Subjection</hi> is to be owned alwayes out of Conſcience. <hi>Obedience</hi> is ſuppoſed to be required in Scripture, in matters wherein the Superiour hath <hi>Authority,</hi> that is, <hi>a right from God to Command.</hi> Such matters being only what is for the <hi>publick good,</hi> thoſe Lawes or Commands which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>that end,</hi> are no Lawes or Commands God bids us obey, that is, are in <hi>ſenſu uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voco</hi> no Lawes: and when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obey in all others, but in thoſe which are Lawes only <hi>ſecundum nomen,</hi> I do <hi>obey him</hi> (I count) <hi>in all things;</hi> becauſe thoſe I diſobey, are none <hi>ſecundum nominis rationem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be perhaps thought upon this, that I ſhould have made a quicker diſpatch of my Work then I do, to ſay that all Lawes do indeed bind the Conſcience (it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perer to ſay do bind in Conſcience), but ſuch Lawes as are not for the common good are <hi>no Lawes.</hi> To which purpoſe may <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Suarez</hi> be conſulted. <hi>Omnium commune axioma eſt de ratione &amp; ſubſtantia legis eſſe, ut pro communi bono feratur.</hi> Suarez, <hi>De legibus l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. You may find Authorities enough there quoted to read at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33146:58"/>your leaſure. I will tranſcribe thus much out of <hi>Cicero</hi> my ſelf. <hi>Principem legem mentem eſſe dicebant omnia ratione aut co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentis aut vetantis dei: ex qua illa lex quam dij humano generi dederunt, recte eſt laudata. Eſt enim ratio menſque ſapientis ad inbendum &amp; ad deterrendum idonea.—Conſtat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto ad ſalutem civium civitatumque incolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatem vitamque omnium quietam &amp; beatam conditas eſſe leges: eoſque qui primum ejuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſcita ſanxerunt, populis oſtendiſſe ea ſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turos atque laturos, quibus illi ad ſcriptis ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptiſque honeſte beateque viverent: quaeque ita compoſita ſanctaque eſſent, eas leges videli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet nominarunt. Ex quo intelligi par eſt, eos qui pernicioſa &amp; injuſta populis juſſa deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerint, cum contra fecerint quam polliciti pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſique ſint, quidvis potius tuliſſe quam leges.</hi> The ſum of both comes to this. <hi>The chief Law is the Divine reaſon; The Lawes of Men muſt be agreeable to that; God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are to make Men happy, by living ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly; Mens Lawes accordingly, that are not for the Peoples welfare, are nothing leſs than what they are called.</hi> To theſe I will joyn <hi>Auguſtine, Iſtas leges, injuſtas vel potius nullas dicemus? Nam mihi lex eſſe non vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quae juſta non fuerit.</hi> Auguſt. <hi>de lib. arb. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. If you ask me then, why I did not go this way, I will tell you, that beſides
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33146:59"/>it looks not ſafe, fit, or civil to ſay, that any thing which is once paſſed into an Act of Parliament is <hi>no Law,</hi> there is a neceſſity you may perceive here, that we muſt come to ſome diſtinction at laſt: and I did chooſe to diſtinguiſh of the <hi>Obligation,</hi> and to ſhew in what ſenſe we are not <hi>obliged,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then of the <hi>Law,</hi> and to ſay in what ſenſe, it is <hi>no Law.</hi> Let Law be defined out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right according to theſe, and, <hi>Law is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the will of the Law-giver, what the Subject is to do for the publick good.</hi> If a Law now be not for the publick utility, it is no Law according to this definition; it hath not that in it which is <hi>de ratione legis,</hi> as the Schools ſpeak. It is a Law therefore in <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu aequivoco</hi> which agrees in the name, but not in <hi>ſenſu univoco,</hi> which participates of the <hi>nature</hi> or the <hi>definition.</hi> To avoid the uſing theſe terms therefore, and in regard ſuch an Act is Law ſtill in <hi>ſome ſenſe,</hi> in the common ſenſe and Vote of the Nation, and in <hi>ſome reſpect</hi> more than aequivocally ſo, becauſe proceeding from a rightful Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it does <hi>in part</hi> agree in the <hi>definition,</hi> as well as in the name, and conſequently <hi>in part</hi> muſt be <hi>Obligatory,</hi> it does appear how the diſtinction does as it were naturally devolve upon the <hi>Obligation:</hi> and ſo ſpares this upon the <hi>Law;</hi> ſeeing if we will truly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33146:59"/>explicate what we mean, when we deny ſuch a Law to be law, this we muſt ſay in good earneſt, and nothing elſe is our mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it is a Law ſo far as to be obeyed for fear of the penalty (for <hi>never to reſiſt</hi> I count in my Book is ſtill pre-required), but not <hi>ſo far,</hi> as that every omiſſion of it is ſin, or that we are obliged to it in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> And thus by going the farther way about, we are but brought the nearer home to the true deciſion we entend. Only one thing I find wanting yet in the explanation of the terms of this diſtinction I uſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Outward Man</hi> and the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> I have been at a good deal of pains to make thoſe received terms currant (Compare my <hi>Obligation of human Lawes</hi> p. 24. with my <hi>Authority of the Magiſtrat</hi> p. 50.) and all I ſee will not ſerve till I diſtinguiſh alſo of <hi>Conſcience</hi> it ſelf, which is taken <hi>Phyſically</hi> or <hi>Theologically.</hi> Conſcience <hi>Naturally</hi> taken is any knowledge of my ſelf or my concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Conſcience taken <hi>Theologically</hi> is the knowledge of what I have to do with Reference to the will and judgement of God, <hi>Judicium de ſemet ipſo prout ſubjicitur judicio dei.</hi> When Divines in this point therefore do diſtinguiſh the <hi>Outward Man</hi> and the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by the Conſcience we muſt underſtand Conſcience in the Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33146:60"/>ſenſe only. That is, we Separate not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Reaſon, Will, Underſtanding, or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ural</hi> Conſcience it Self from the <hi>Outward Man,</hi> but Conſcience only <hi>Theologically</hi> taken. And the Meaning is plainly, that though a Man in Reaſon underſtands, and is Conſcious in regard to his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernement, that ſuch a Law is to be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, if he will avoid this or that Penalty or Inconvenience: Yet ſo long as he Believes God does not Command him to do it, and that he ſhall incurr no Diſpleaſure from him though he omits it, this is to be Obliged in the <hi>Outward Man</hi> only, and not in <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Conſcience taken <hi>Naturally,</hi> not <hi>Theologically</hi> in Conſcience.</p>
            <p>After I had wrote this and all the reſt, (only ſomthing I hereupon inſerted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore), I had Dr. <hi>Field</hi> on the Church acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentaly brought me. It was many years ſince I read him, and I had forgot every thing in him on this Subject but only his Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> which I like, and ever retained. I am well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to find my <hi>genius</hi> agreeing ſo much as it does with one of ſo great Note and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; eſpecially ſeeing that Tenet which <hi>Dean</hi> F. oppoſes as mine is that alone in effect wherein our Sentiments meet not. <hi>You ſay</hi> (ſayes <hi>Dean</hi> F.) <hi>when a thing is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33146:60"/>Commanded of God, or we think it tends to the Publick good, then only Conſcience is Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: But this Obligation is only from the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the thing Commanded, &amp; becauſe you approve it to be a Duty before, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Obedience to your own Reaſon, and not at all out of Conſcience of the Command, or in Obedience to the King.</hi> Well! Let us then hear Dr. <hi>Field,</hi> a greater Dean, deliver his judgment: Which I will ſet down in his words at large for the Readers Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The queſtion ſhould not be propoſed, whether Humane Laws bind the Conſcience (This he takes up in the Negative as not to be queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed): but whether binding the outward Man to the performance of outward things by force and fear of outward Puniſhment to be inflicted by men, the not performance of ſuch things, (or the not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rformance of them with ſuch affections as were fit) be not a Sin againſt God of which the Conſcience will accuſe us, he having Commanded us to Obey the Magiſtrates and Rulers he hath ſet over us! For anſwer hereunto, there are three ſorts of things</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>Commanded by Magiſtrates.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Evil and againſt God.</hi> Secondly <hi>Injurious in reſpect of them to whom they are Preſcribed, or at leaſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable to the Common-Wealth in which they are Preſcribed.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>ſuch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33146:61"/>as are Profitable and Beneficial to the Society of Men to whom they are Preſcribed. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Firſt Sort of things, We muſt not Obey. Touching the ſecond Sort of things, all that God requireth of us is that we ſhew no contempt of Sacred Authority though not rightly uſed, that we Scandalize not others, and that we he Subject to ſuch Penaltyes, as they that Command ſuch things do lay upon us. In the Third Sort of things, it is only that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires our Willing and ready Obedience. The Breach and Violation of this kind of Laws is Sin, not for that humane Laws have Power to Bind the Conſcience, or that it is ſimply and abſolutely ſinful to break them, but becauſe the things they Command are of that Nature that not to perform them, is contrary to Juſtice, Charity, and the deſire we ſhould have to procure the Common-Good of them with whom we Live. We are bound then ſomtimes to the Performance of things preſcribed by Humane Laws in ſuch Sort that the not Performance of them is Sin; not</hi> ex ſola Legiſlatoris voluntate, ſed ex ipſa legum utilitate, <hi>as</hi> Stapleton <hi>Rightly obſerved. But ſome Man will ſay, what do the Laws then effect ſeeing it is the Law of Juſtice, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that doth bind us, and not the Particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Laws newly Made! To this we anſwer that many things are God and Profitable, if they be generally Obſerved, which without ſuch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33146:61"/>general Obſervation will do no Good. The Law procureth a general Obſervation.</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine <hi>objects, Be ſubject for Conſcience Sake. To this we anſwer.</hi> Firſt. <hi>That it is a matter of Conſcience to be</hi> Subject <hi>in all things, for</hi> Subjection <hi>is required Generally and Abſolutely where</hi> Obedience <hi>is Not.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly. <hi>We ſay that it is a matter of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Seek and Procure the Good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth, and that therefore it is a matter of Conſcience to obey Good and Profitable Laws, ſo farr as we are perſwaded our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is profitable.</hi> Moreover, <hi>General and Long continued Diſuſe is, and Juſtly may be thought an Aboliſhing, and Abrogating of Humane Laws. For ſeeing</hi> Lex inſtitutitur cum promulgatur, vigorem habet cum mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus utentium approbatur. <hi>On the Church Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>I muſt remember my Antogoniſt to take Notice that <hi>What</hi> he goes to oppoſe in me as ſome ſingular Opinion of mine, which yet is not mine, but he miſtakes me in it, is Preſented by this Great <hi>Dr.</hi> of the Church as the received Doctrine of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: As alſo, that the Doctrine which in deed is mine, &amp; this <hi>Dr</hi> agrees ſo much with me, does require his better Conſideration.</p>
            <p>J. H's. <hi>Second Principle is that Human Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may not lawfully Command or Inforce any
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33146:62"/>thing againſt the Conſcience, even in Civil Concernes.</hi> He ſhould have ſaid in things that are materially <hi>Civil,</hi> yet under ſome Conſideration unto ſome <hi>Religious.</hi> What the Magiſtrate cannot Command (I ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) he cannot Inforce. The Magiſtrate cannot Command what God forbids. God forbids every Man to do any thing againſt his Conſcience. And what hath any Mortal to oppoſe againſt this? Why, he has one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument only, which he takes from my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, in the ſtating my Matter. I Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between a Man's doing <hi>according to his Conſcience,</hi> and his doing <hi>againſt It;</hi> and of <hi>Reſtraint</hi> and <hi>Conſtraint</hi> accordingly in the Magiſtrate. I grant that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may <hi>Reſtraine</hi> a man from doing <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Conſcience</hi> when he is doing hurt to Church or State through his errour, and may Puniſh him for the Evil he does: He argues from hence that he may <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine</hi> him to doe that which is Good for the Church or State, though it be <hi>againſt his Conſcience,</hi> upon the ſame account. But I ſay, not. There is a Difference. I give my Reaſon. <hi>Becauſe in the one, the Man does what God would not have him: In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he does what God would have. God would not have him to do Evil, becauſe of his erroneous Conſcience, but that he ſhould lay
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33146:62"/>down his Errour and do Good: But God will have every Man ſo to regard his Conſcience though Eerroneous, that he muſt not do any thing againſt it, for any Fear, or Advantage in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eaerth.</hi> Author. of the Mag. <hi>Pag.</hi> 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. And what anſwer makes he to this Reaſon! Why not a word. So overly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> men ordinarily to ſpeak at the firſt ſight againſt that, which others have thought long upon. The ſubſtance of the Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo of my Detemination, I cited out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and confirmed it with <hi>Grotius</hi> his Approbation. I might add to them the Learned <hi>Rutherford,</hi> who are Judicious mighty Men all three, but this Gentle <hi>Dean</hi> hath not Pondred the Matter. For thus he proceeds. <hi>The Law of God is the Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience. This Law is Negative as well as Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, and binds the Conſcience equally in both reſpects. So far we are Agreed.</hi> Hold Sir! A miſtake again. He forgets the known Rule in the Schools, that Affirmations bind <hi>Semper,</hi> not <hi>ad Semper,</hi> not to all times, or in all Caſes: but <hi>Negatives</hi> do bind <hi>Semper</hi> and <hi>ad Semper,</hi> alwayes, and againſt all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions. He remembers not himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when he ſaies they <hi>Bind equally,</hi> and ſo thinks not how the Deciſion of the Point muſt reſolve into this Iſſue. In the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative Caſe I ſay it is true, that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33146:63"/>the Man to lay down his Errour, and not to do the thing, and therefore the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may <hi>Restrain,</hi> or Puniſh him: In the <hi>Negative caſe</hi> he urges likewiſe, God commands him the Same as to laying down his Errour, and to do the thing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he may <hi>Conſtraine</hi> or make him. But I reply no ſtill, the difference remains. Though in the <hi>Negative caſe</hi> (that is, when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is Erroneous ſayes they muſt not do ſuch a thing) God requires this <hi>Joyntly,</hi> to lay down his Erroneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (or be other-wiſe informed), and to do the thing, yet does not he require this <hi>Separately,</hi> that while he is ſo informed, he ſhould do it: When in the affirmative Caſe (that is when the Conſcience which is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, ſaies thou muſt do ſuch or ſuch a thing) God requires he ſhould lay down his Errour &amp; not do the thing both <hi>Joyntly and Separately;</hi> ſo that even while he is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his Conſcience that it is his Duty, God's Negative Command is Obligatory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Perſwaſion. The reaſon is from what is Said, becauſe Affirmatives do not bind <hi>ad Semper,</hi> or in all Caſes, but <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> do. This is one of thoſe Caſes. <hi>Thou ſhalt not do againſt thy Conſcience,</hi> is a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> Indiſpenſable: <hi>Thou ſhalt do accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it,</hi> holds not in this Caſe, when the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33146:63"/>Conſcience is in an Errour.</p>
            <p>I will conclude with the Hiſtory of this little I have written. There is a Book call'd <hi>the Friendly Debate,</hi> which when it came out was received every where with diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of acceptation, and cenſure. There are many things in it I am perſwaded in my heart fit to be ſpoken: yet do I not know, nor the Authour himſelf perhaps know from what <hi>manner of Spirit</hi> they are ſpoken. It is in appearance a Spirit elated, contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, engaged (if not imbitterd) againſt a party, and ſo far un-Catholick, which does through the ſides of that party oftentimes make Religion her ſelf <hi>feel,</hi> entrenching upon it almoſt all the way, in regard to thoſe weakneſſes and follies which Human reaſon is ever ready to impute to it. <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the World to confound the Wiſe: and the things that are deſpiſed hath he choſen.</hi> Among other matters againſt the Non-Conformiſts, that Authour brings this, that they obſerve not the Lawes, the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act, and others, and that therefore they <hi>cannot be good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, nor good Chriſtians, nor Miniſters of Chriſt.</hi> A heavy charge, and a neceſſary caſe of Conſcience! Upon this occaſion I preſented to the publick a ſheet called the <hi>Caſe</hi> under this Title. <hi>Whether a Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33146:64"/>who hath not taken the</hi> Oxford <hi>Oath, might come to live at</hi> London,, <hi>or any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate Town, or within Five miles of it, and yet be a good Chriſtian?</hi> To this Sheet the Authour was pleaſed to give me an Anſwer. That Anſwer drew me forth to write my Book by way of reply, <hi>of the Obligation of human Lawes.</hi> To this reply the learned Debater anſwered no more. After the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</hi> another peice comes forth of <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Polity,</hi> exceeding the former both in Pomp and Deſign, in Luſtre and the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; that was for aſſerting an <hi>Authority</hi> in the Magiſtrate <hi>over the Conſcience</hi> to end all Diſputes, which being a thing not to be endured, though but in the matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, as the Authour I think only meant, I wrote alſo my other Book, <hi>of the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Magiſtrate about Religion.</hi> Unto this Book I had no anſwer from that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour neither: Only having cauſed thoſe few Copies which were left of the <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in Quires to be Bound up with this, and Printing ſo many on purpoſe of the Sheet called <hi>The Caſe</hi> over again, to fit and joyn to both, and then Entituled it, <hi>Two points of great moment Diſcuſſed,</hi> I do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that it hath pleaſed this Reverend Dean to ſtep in with theſe Two exceptions of his, which I have anſwered: and one
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33146:64"/>thing more in the cloſe muſt not paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded, which he brings in under the head of the former of the Two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Obligation</hi> (of I. H.) <hi>is only from neceſſity of the thing commanded. But in all other caſes you need not obey only for wraths ſake, that is, no farther then you are forced; and therefore when you are got above fears you will not, or need not, regard Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. This principle will hardly prove the Non-Conformiſts the only Loyaliſts.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the miſtake before noted. It is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but want of the preſent knowledge, in this <hi>Dr</hi> as it was in the <hi>Debater,</hi> of the diſtinction I offered them out of Dr <hi>Field,</hi> between <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> or the ſenſe of it, that made them fall into ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſort of reaſoning, as this is. Though there be many caſes, wherein we are not bound in Conſcience to <hi>Obey:</hi> yet are we alwayes bound in Conſcience to be <hi>Subject,</hi> or never to <hi>Reſiſt,</hi> and upon that ground is our <hi>Loyalty</hi> maintained. This I have ſaid, I know moſt effectually in my <hi>firſt Book</hi> of the Two Points, unto which, therefore, when that which is brought to its Aſſiſtance in the <hi>Second,</hi> and this little in theſe <hi>Two Sheets</hi> now more is added (which I would by no means have thoſe, who have the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33146:65"/>other be without), there is nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, as <hi>I</hi> can find in my mind (unleſs to tell the Reader, leaſt he be at a loſs, that there are a few of theſe <hi>Two Poynts</hi> ſo bound up, yet to be had, at the <hi>Golden Lyon</hi> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s-<hi>Church-yard</hi>) that is lacking to my full ſatisfaction on thoſe Subjects,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale Lector &amp; fruere Deo gloria.</salute> 
               <signed>I. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33146:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
